<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bonasus vapulans, or, Some castigations given to Mr. John Durell for fouling himself and others in his English and Latin book by a country scholar.</title>
            <author>Hickman, Henry, d. 1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 190 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 70 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43711</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1908</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34462</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14445173</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14445173</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102358</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43711)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102358)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1060:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Bonasus vapulans, or, Some castigations given to Mr. John Durell for fouling himself and others in his English and Latin book by a country scholar.</title>
                  <author>Hickman, Henry, d. 1692.</author>
                  <author>Durel, John, 1625-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 150 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Hickman.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages faded.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102358:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102358:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>BONAS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S VAP<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LANS:</hi> OR, Some Caſtigations given to Mr. <hi>John Durell,</hi> for fouling himſelf and others in his Engliſh and Latin Book.</p>
            <p>By a Country Scholar.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1672.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:102358:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:102358:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:102358:3"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 3. l. 25. r. <hi>reproved</hi> p. 12. l. 15. r. <hi>bear.</hi> p. 13. l. 16. r. <hi>hasp.</hi> 16 l. 7. r. <hi>whether.</hi> p. 21. l. 18. r. <hi>nor ſhould have.</hi> p. 26. l. 26. r. <hi>Phraſes. In ons.</hi> p. 28. l. 21. r. <hi>Salmurienſes.</hi> p. 30. l. 17. r. <hi>operous.</hi> p. 39, l. 25. &amp; 41. l. 10. r. <hi>Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt.</hi> p. 44. l. 22. r. <hi>That,</hi> &amp; l. ult r. <hi>there is.</hi> p. 49. l. antepen. r. <hi>the more.</hi> p. 53 l. 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Tithes.</hi> p. 59. l. ult. r. <hi>bring us.</hi> p. 63. l. 25. r. <hi>there called</hi> p. 64. l 26. r. <hi>world.</hi> p 72. l. 21. r. <hi>was.</hi> l. 25. r. <hi>Aquila.</hi> p 79. l. 1. r. <hi>of ſuch.</hi> l. 9. r. <hi>ſtrongly.</hi> l. 17. r. <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> p. 94. l. 26. r. <hi>Conſecration, though</hi> p. 114. l. 7. r. <hi>there</hi> p. 119. l. 3. r. <hi>all</hi> p 128. l. 3. r. <hi>in</hi> p. 136. l. 20. r. <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae</hi> p. 138. l. 20. r. <hi>down; and</hi> p. 145. l. 13. r. <hi>will find</hi> p. ult. l. 10. r. <hi>in the behalf of</hi> l. 11. r. <hi>done, you will.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102358:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve of late ſo wholly addicted my ſelf to practical Theology, and taken ſo huge a pleaſure, in reading thoſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors that never eſpouſed the petty inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the Times, that next to wiſhing for Mr. <hi>Durell</hi>'s ſake, his Eriſtical volume had never been written, I wiſh for my own ſake you had never ſent it me, or at leaſt ſent it me under ſuch circumſtances, that I might have laid it down aſſoon as it had given me enough of it, <hi>i. e.</hi> as ſoon as I had read the Title page. Certainly if you had left me to pay the Stationer for it, if I had not returned it, it ſhould only have ſtood in my Library, to encreaſe the number of my Books: nor ſhould I have ever taken it down, unleſs when I take down <hi>Bonarſcius</hi> his <hi>Amphitheatrum,</hi> i. e. when I have a mind to diſcover unto my ſelf, or others, unto what a height of bitterneſs, corrupt nature, not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by Grace, will tranſport men even in controverſies relating to Religion; which of all others require to be managed with exemplary moderation and meekneſs: but
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102358:4"/>
ſeeing you have thought meet to be ſo bountiful as to beſtow a Book on me, which muſt needs coſt you ſundry ſhillings: and ſeeing you have deſired of me (for a requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal of your coſt and charges) to throw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſome time upon it, I ſhould be extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uncivil and unthankful, if I ſhould not beſtow a few hours in reading of it, or ſo much of it, as may be ſufficient to paſs a judgement upon the whole, the which yet I cannot ſo well do, until I have firſt given my cenſure of that Engliſh Treatiſe printed, 1662 the anſwering whereof in a Latin Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy for the Nonconformiſts, has produced theſe voluminous <hi>Vindiciae,</hi> and of that Treatiſe my cenſure in brief is this, that a Noncomformiſt cannot better ſecure himſelf againſt it, then by ſtanding at the mark, at the which its Author pretends to ſhoot all his Arrows; The controverſies betwixt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts and Non-Conformiſts being brought to their true State, it will appear that Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> either never knew them, or was afraid to come near them: To inſtance in a few particulars of many.</p>
            <p>Several hundreds of Miniſters during the late diſtractions, were ordained by meer Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, they only having courage enough to confer orders publickly, and ſolemnly with <hi>Faſting, Prayer</hi> and <hi>impoſition of hands:</hi> None
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102358:4"/>
of theſe would the Biſhops admit to Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical employment, unleſs they would ſubmit to be re-ordained with and by that very form of Ordination, which is uſed for the Tranſlating of Laicks into the ſtate of Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gymen: Here two Queſtions ariſe, firſt, Whether a valid Ordination may be repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? and that the far greater part as well of Conformiſts, as Non-Conformiſts deny: the ſecond therefore and only remaining Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, Whether an Ordination by meer Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters be valid? if it be not, we nullifie the moſt famous Churches beyond the Seas, whom God has ſo remarkably owned and ſupported amid all the troubles and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions of their Popiſh Adverſaries; if it be valid, then by the judgement even of the very Conformiſts, no other Ordination can be received: Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> was unwilling to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilate thoſe Churches in which he was bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, and yet was as unwilling to juſtifie the Engliſh Presbyterians in not ſubmitting to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination, and therefore wiſely paſſed over theſe Queſtions in ſilence; but being by the Latin Apologiſt reprove for omitting ſo Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital a controverſie, he grows more hardy, and adventures to affirm the Caſe of the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians beyond the Sea, and thoſe in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> is not the ſame: becauſe among them there are no Biſhops, as among ours there
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102358:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
were, and ſo they are defended by neceſſity, which ours cannnot plead. How much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter had it been to have left this ſore naked and expoſed to the Eyes of all, than to have uſed a Plaiſter that can neither Cure, nor cover it? Is the Caſe of Tranſmarine and Engliſh Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians ſo vaſtly different? Why is the ſame hard meaſure meeted out to both? How comes it to paſs, that if a man ordained at <hi>Rome,</hi> could obtain leave of himſelf to aſſent and conſent, he were capable of the higheſt Eccleſiaſtical dignities: but if a man were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained at <hi>Geneva,</hi> the moſt unfeigned aſſent and conſent will not qualify him for Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical dignities, unleſs he will alſo receive new Orders. Was it ſo from the beginning either of our firſt or ſecond Reformations? were any of thoſe, that either in the perſecutions of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, or Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> fled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, and received orders in reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches, looked upon at their return as meer Lay-men? our Hiſtories tell us they were not: nor would the right Reverend and Learned Biſhop <hi>Morton</hi> ſo far ſcandalize the Neighbour Churches, as to re-ordain one of their Miniſters, though ſtrongly importuned ſo to do, by a Letter of the diſſembling Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Spalato.</hi> Nor could Biſhop <hi>Bán<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croft</hi> be induced to give way, that the Scotch Divines ſhould firſt be made Prieſts before
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102358:5"/>
they were Biſhops, although it was alleadged that they had never been made Prieſts, but by Presbyters. So as this cuſtom of Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying <hi>de novo</hi> thoſe that before had received the gift of Presbytery, muſt needs be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation here in <hi>England:</hi> of the which I wiſh I could give a more fair and plauſible ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count unto Forreigners, then for the preſent I am able; For it would greatly diſhearten thoſe renowned Miniſters abroad, who live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a King of a different Religion from them, to come over to our Nation for a Sanctuary, if they muſt when come hither, break the Seal that God hath ſet to their Miniſtry, before they be admitted to any cure of Souls.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſay this pretended difference is no difference at all, for what though there were Biſhops in <hi>England,</hi> yet did they not appear to magnifie their offices And it hath been wont to be accounted the ſame thing not <hi>to be,</hi> and not <hi>to appear:</hi> and if they had <hi>appeared,</hi> their <hi>appearance</hi> might perhaps make thoſe Presbyters who gave orders without them <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> it could not poſſible make their orders <hi>null:</hi> for as formerly where our Church thought that Baptiſme adminiſtred by a Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife was valid, and allowed and enjoyned her in Caſe of neceſſity to baptize, the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife had offended, if ſhe had baptized where there was no true neceſſity; yet this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102358:6"/>
offence notwithſtanding, her baptiſme would have been reputed valid: ſo here, if our Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters could confer a valid Ordination, when Biſhops were not at hand, their Ordination muſt needs be <hi>valid,</hi> though Biſhops were at hand; &amp; therefore all the duſt that is raiſed by Mr. <hi>D.</hi> to ſhew ſome difference between the Presbyters of our own and other Churches, could be deſigned to no other end, but to blind his own and his Readers Eyes, that ſo no notice might be taken how he got off this controverſie: it may be he may come nearer the mark in the point of Epiſcopacy it ſelf, but of that alſo we ſhall find that his Arrows fall Heavenly wide: For the Non-Conformiſt has again and again profeſſed in conference and writing, that he can and would for peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake receive a Biſhop, that ſhould have as great a ſuperintendence over Presbyters as ever <hi>Cyprian</hi> had over his, but they ſay that by aſſenting and conſenting to the preſent Book of Ordination, they muſt acknowledge a Biſhop to be by <hi>divine Inſtitution, of a ſuperiour order</hi> to a <hi>Presbyter;</hi> and for this they ſay they can find no Foundation in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and leſs then none in any writings of modern reformed Divines: If they are mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken either in ſetting our Biſhops higher then they have ſet themſelves, or in making a Biſhop when ſet to ſuch a heighth, to be an
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102358:6"/>
Officer unknown to Primitive or Modern Churches, Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> had done a very Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian work: if he had taken pains in the Spirit of meekneſs, to ſhew them their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake: but he cannot ſure think that he hath endeavoured any ſuch thing: <q>He tells us page 4th. and the 5th. that all the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Churches have a ſubordination of Paſtours, and that thoſe who are in them called Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintendents, or Biſhops, have the power of Ordination as the Biſhops of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But does he believe what he himſelf writes? does he not know that they all found their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintendency on a human and not on a divine inſtitution? does he not know that ſome <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran</hi> Divines of eminent note, do with full mouth declaim againſt us here in <hi>England,</hi> becauſe we ſo much appropriate the power of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation unto Biſhops? <hi>Tobias Major</hi> I am ſure on this very ſcore calls us <hi>Angli Papizantes:</hi> let all Scholars conſult <hi>Chemnitius, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard, Brockmand,</hi> or any other <hi>Lutheran</hi> that writes common places, or if they be too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to conſult, let them conſult <hi>Hunnius</hi>'s de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Miniſtry, in which they ſhall find him, though himſelf a Superintendent, making a Biſhop in Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to act only as the Churches inſtrument; and averring, that if the Church ſhould dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102358:7"/>
her power to a Presbyter, or to a Layman, the Ordination would be as valid, as if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by a Biſhop. The Non-Conformiſts have no quarrel againſt the <hi>name,</hi> either of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintendent or Biſhop, nor will it be any ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to them, to ſhew them Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Perſons in the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Churches, digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the name of Superintendents or Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copi, unleſs it could alſo be ſhewed, that they claim that dignity by divine right, and are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Elders, as an <hi>Order</hi> of men ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour to them: the which will never be ſhewed: nay it will eaſily be proved, that meer Presbyters have ordained thoſe who in <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Denmark</hi> go by the name of Biſhops and Super-intendents: <hi>Nicholas, Amsdorft,</hi> as appears in his Life written by <hi>Melchior Adam,</hi> was created Biſhop; but by whom was he created? by <hi>Martin Luther</hi> the Paſtour of the place where the Ordination was ſolemnized, and two Paſtours more. Now did theſe ſet this Biſhop into an order ſuperiour to their own? if they did, who gave them authority ſo to do? if they did not, then his Title notwithſtanding he was ſtill of the <hi>Order</hi> of Presbyters, and thoſe that were afterwards ordained by him, were ordained but by a Presbyter. Likewiſe in <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> when Reformation there firſt began, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Biſhops of the Kingdome being caſt out,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102358:7"/>
there were ſeven Super-intendents ordained, who were to do the work of the expelled Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and to be Executors of the whole Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Ordination; but by whom were theſe ſeven ordained? even by <hi>John Bugenhagh,</hi> who was but a Presbyter, as may be ſeen in his Life, written by the forementioned Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor; ſo that ſuch Epiſcopacy as is ſcrupled by the Engliſh Non-Conformiſt, has no place in any <hi>Lutheran</hi> Churches: and if not in the <hi>Lutheran,</hi> I am ſure not in the reformed Churches.</p>
            <p>Yet Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> in many places of his Book, makes ſhew as if the Epiſcopacy quarrelled againſt here in <hi>England,</hi> had place in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, and that thoſe very Churches among whoſe Miniſters there is an equality, do not condemn Epiſcopal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: the French Churches he is certain page 13. <q>are ſo far from averſeneſs to it, that they rather wiſh they were in a condition to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy that ſacred order.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now what means he by that <hi>ſacred Order?</hi> if he do not mean an Order by Divine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, ſuperiour to the order of Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, he doth moſt egregiouſly trifle; If he do mean ſuch an Order, I ſay that as many French Divines as do deſire ſuch an Order, are manifeſtly fallen off from the confeſſion exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited to <hi>Charles</hi> 9th. 1561. the 30th. Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle whereof is this.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:102358:8"/>
               <q>We believe that all true Paſtours in what place ſo ever they are ſet, are all endued with the ſame and equal power among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, under that one head and chief and ſole univerſal Biſhop Jeſus Chriſt.</q> And if any Miniſters of the Belgick Churches do either deſire or could approve of the Engliſh Hierarchy, they alſo muſt fall off from the Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick Confeſſion, which in the Synod of <hi>Dort</hi> was reviewed and approved: for if that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, had no inimicous aſpect upon the Church Government in <hi>Britain,</hi> why did our Divines of <hi>England</hi> approve only that part of it, which related to Doctrine, not that which related to Diſcipline?</p>
            <p>Our Prelates and their Friends in <hi>England</hi> do very much build their Hierarchy upon <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius</hi> his Epiſtles. If the French Churches did not diſlike the building, why do the moſt Learned of them take ſo much pains to ruine and pull up the Foundation? why have <hi>Blon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del, Salmaſius, Dally,</hi> ſo long employed their Pens to prove the Epiſtles even in the beſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to be ſpurious; I know Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> tells a ſtory concerning <hi>Blondel,</hi> that in his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy for the opinion of <hi>Hierom,</hi> he had inſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a paſſage, which ſome Scotch Miniſters prevailed with him to blot out: in which he declares himſelf to be no Enemy unto Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Epiſcopacy: if that be true, he did not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102358:8"/>
ſure think our Epiſcopacy to be Primitive, for Doctor <hi>Hammond</hi> in his Anſwer to <hi>Blondel</hi> complains of him, <hi>as if he were ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing touched with any care of our Church, or ſenſe of our miſeries, that he thought meet contrarily more ſharply to prick thoſe that were already oppreſſed, and endeavoured to triumph over our Church when it was ſick and ſtaggering, and ready by reaſon of inward troubles to give up the Ghoſt;</hi> let Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> now conſider, whether he will make his Countryman <hi>Blondell</hi> an Enemy to our Hierarchy, or make our Countryman Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> a Calumniatour; one of the two he muſt unavoidably do: And for the future let him bethink himſelf how to wipe off that great and black blot, which he hath let fall upon ſome of the beſt and moſt obedient of the Sons of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> page 2. <q>
                  <hi>viz.</hi> that they <hi>weakly</hi> ſuffered themſelves to be brought into a bad and falſe opinion of the Tranſmarine reformed Churches, mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly by the reports given them by the new Presbyterians.</q>
            </p>
            <p>For certainly it is little to their credit, when they had the Confeſſions and Symbolical Books of the reformed Churches in their Libraries, never to conſult them, but to take up reports concerning their Neighbours, from Men, whoſe intereſt did lead them to make the world believe, that they had a many Friends a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102358:9"/>
though but few at home. Doubtleſs our Epiſcopal Divines knew well enough, that the Hierarchy they aimed at was not counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced by Siſter-Churches; and long before <hi>Smectymnuus</hi> was heard of, or ever ſuch a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as an Ordinance of Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſaw the light, one among us had ſaid publickly, <hi>perfecto odio odi. Calvinum:</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi> had inured his tongue to ſay <hi>Eccleſia Romana,</hi> and <hi>Turba Genevenſis:</hi> he had alſo told Biſhop <hi>Hall,</hi> that though he did well to put a difference betwixt the Scottiſh and other Churches, yet he had written more favourably even of other Churches, than their cauſe would then bare; and the good cauſe then in hand did work ſo powerfully even up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Holy and Learned Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that he adventured, as Mr. <hi>Prin</hi> tells us, to reordain Mr. <hi>John Dury,</hi> though he had been before ordained in ſome Reformed Church. Such an Epiſcopacy as was claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Arch-biſhop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> the far greater part at leaſt of preſent Non-Conformiſts could admit but ſuch an Epiſcopacy as Arch-biſhop <hi>Laud</hi> was introducing they cannot yet digeſt, and that is the Epiſcopacy that the preſent book of Ordination, if aſſented and conſented unto, would engage us in: and let it not ſeem ſtrange that the preſent Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts ſtartle at it, when as Dr. <hi>Holland</hi> the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102358:9"/>
Kings profeſſour of Divinity in <hi>Oxford,</hi> was ſo much offended with Dr. <hi>Laud</hi> for aſſerting it, that he did not ſtick to affirm he was a Schiſmatick, and went about to make a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion betwixt the Engliſh and other Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches: yet though the Non-Conformiſts do not like ſuch a kind of Hierarchy, they will if they conſult the peace of their Conſciences, uſe no ſuch incivil language againſt it as ſome of Mr. <hi>Durells</hi> Countrymen have done: they will not be ſo uncivil as to call Dr. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> Knave, which is the Engliſh to <hi>Salma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> his <hi>Nebulo:</hi> they will not ſay as <hi>Mare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> does in his Examen of Dr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> his four Queſtions, pag. 1. <q>That Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> as proceeded to ſuch a degree of fury, as <hi>profeſſedly to propugne the cauſe of the Pope.</hi> Much leſs will they ſay that the Engliſh Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops had better conſulted their eminence, if they had acted more moderately in it, and had rather with the reſt of Proteſtants made it to be of humane inſtitution, than ſo ſtifly to aſſert the <hi>jus divinum</hi> of it: for as a bow by too much bending of it is broken, ſo they too much ſtretching their Authority and dignity fell, quite from it, like the Camel in the Fable, who becauſe he affected horns loſt his ears, pag. 68. leaſt of all will they ſay, as the ſame Author ſays pag. 71.</q> (which I tremble to Engliſh) <q>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſules
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102358:10"/>
Angli ex parte collimarunt ad Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmi reſtitutionem jure poſtliminii: <hi>and pag. 111.</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t dicam quod res est, haec defenſio tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralis Jurisdictionis pro Eccleſiae Miniſtris por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio aliqua eſt illius fermenti Papiſtici quo Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchiae Anglicanae maſſa paulatim ſe infici paſſa fuit, dum magis ambit Typhum Seculi, quam humilitatem Crucis meditatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude all, when the Learned <hi>Gata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> was moſt bitterly railed upon by <hi>Lilly</hi> for being a Presbyterian, he anſwers in his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, pag. 24. <q>A duly bounded and well regulated Prelacy, joyned with a Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, wherein one as Preſident, Superinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, Moderator (term him what you pleaſe) whether Annual or Occaſional, or more conſtant and continual, either in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of years or parts, or both jointly, hath ſome preheminence above the reſt, yet ſo, as that he do nothing without joint conſent of the reſt: Such a Prelacy I never durſt, nor yet dare condemn.</q> The like he ſays for divers others, if not the greater part of the Aſſembly, pag. 26. And the ſame dare I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to ſay, in reference to the far greater part of the preſent ſuffering Miniſters; nay I may further undertake for them, that if any one ſhould publiſh in print, that the difference betwixt a Biſhop and Presbyter is by divine inſtitution, they would not think themſelves
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102358:10"/>
any way concerned to have ſuch a one ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended from his Miniſtry: yet if my memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry greatly fail me not, Mounſieur <hi>Peter Mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle to Biſhop <hi>Andrews,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Apology for ſome paſſages in his Tract of the Vocation of Paſtors, excepted againſt by K. <hi>James,</hi> uſeth theſe or the like words; That if he had made the difference betwixt a Biſhop and Presbyter to be founded on a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Law, his own Churches would have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted Eccleſiaſtical cenſures upon him.</p>
            <p>It will concern Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> highly, either to prove that <hi>Moulin</hi> wronged his own Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, or that they have abated of their zeal againſt Epiſcopy; for if he prove neither of theſe, he will loſe (that which is better then all his Eccleſiaſtical revenues) a good name, and when his hand is in at this work, he may alſo do well to take Biſhop <hi>Mountague</hi> to task, who in his appeal to <hi>Caeſar</hi> by his Majeſties ſpecial direction and command peruſed by Dr. <hi>White,</hi> and approved as fit to be Printed, ſays p. 70. <q>That the Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in the Synod of <hi>Dort,</hi> and other Dutch Synods is held unlawful.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If it be held unlawful in the Synod of <hi>Dort,</hi> it may be preſumed it was held unlawful by almoſt all other Reformed Churches; for, almoſt all ſent thither their Delegates: and theſe Delegates approved the confeſſion of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102358:11"/>
Faith, in which onely the Diſcipline of our Church can be thought to be condemned. Now let Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> bid his zeal awake, for certainly <hi>Hannibal eſt ad portas:</hi> either he or Biſhop <hi>Mountague</hi> will be found falſe witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes againſt the Reformed Churches, I will not determine whither muſt be branded for a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminator. Biſhop <hi>Carleton</hi> hath written an examination of <hi>Mountagues</hi> appeal, And pag. 111. gives us to underſtand, <q>That inſtead of yielding his conſent to that ſtrange con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of the parity of Miniſters to be inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by Chriſt, which was inſerted into the Belgick Confeſſion; he openly proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his diſſent thereunto:</q> And I believe that ſuch proteſtation was by him made in his own name, and the name of thoſe ſent out of <hi>England</hi> with him. But I would willingly be ſatisfied, why the Divines of other Churches did not make ſuch proteſtation alſo? Did they think the parity of Miniſters a ſtrange conceit? If they did not, down falls the whole ſtructure of Mr. <hi>Durells</hi> Book: if they did, why did they enter no diſſent to this ſtrange conceit? And I would alſo be ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, what might move our Reverend and Learned <hi>Carleton</hi> to ſay, That the cauſe of all the troubles in the Belgick Church was this, That they had not Biſhops amongſt them, who by their Authority might repreſs thoſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102358:11"/>
who brought in novelties. Sure I am, that not long after the ſitting of that Synod, the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minian</hi> novelties were broached to purpoſe in <hi>England,</hi> and yet we who wanted not Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, either would not, or could not, repreſs the broachers of them. This Reverend Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late was <hi>Dioceſan</hi> to Mr. <hi>Mountague,</hi> who made it his buſineſs to infect us with <hi>Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſm:</hi> If his Epiſcopal power were ſo ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign an Antidote againſt the ſpreading of this infection, why did he never make uſe of it? or how came it to have ſo little ſucceſs? Oh that it were not too manifeſt, that errours may grow in a Reformed Church where Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy is eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>I have one thing more to add which it may not be amiſs here to relate. The Miniſters of the Palatinate being brought into a great deal of diſtreſs, his late Majeſty thought meet under the Broad Seal, to grant them a Collection here in <hi>England</hi> for their Relief. The Letters Patents being Sealed, Archbiſhop <hi>Laud</hi> thought meet to have an Alteration made, in the form of the Letters, and obtained of the King to have it made. It had been ſaid, that the Miniſters extream miſeries fell upon them for their ſincerity and conſtancy in the true Religion, which we together with them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, and becauſe they would not ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Antichriſtian yoke: our moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102358:12"/>
Primate thought not meet to have Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery call'd the Antichriſtian Yoke, though it had been ſo called here in <hi>England</hi> by Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as great as himſelf. Nor did it reliſh with him, that the Religion of the Palatinate Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſhould be called the ſame with ours. Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> in the Hiſtory of his Life, pag. 306. gives the reaſon: <q>Becauſe by the Religion of thoſe Churches the <hi>Calvinian</hi> rigors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Predeſtination, &amp;c. are received as Orthodox, and becauſe they maintain a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Miniſters directly contrary both to the Doctrine and Government of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </q> Either therefore what Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> ſaith from the Palatinate Miniſters in favour of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hierarchy is a meer falſity, or elſe there is ſome ſuch Alteration made in the Judgment of thoſe men of late, as the world formerly knew not of; or elſe the Archbiſhop and his Second laid to the charge of the Palatinate Miniſters, what they were not truly to be charged with.</p>
            <p>I have inſiſted too long on this point, and ſhall conclude it with a profeſſion of my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, that if a <hi>Synod</hi> ſhould be called, made up of the moſt ſober forreign Divines, they would adviſe his Majeſty to eſtabliſh a moderated, limited Epiſcopacy, as more ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Generality of our Engliſh tempers, than that Presbytery which the two Houſes,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102358:12"/>
to ſatisfie the importunities of the Sects, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther made a ſhew they would eſtabliſh, then did eſtabliſh: but I can as ſoon believe they would publiſh to the whole world their own Hypocriſie, as adviſe to ſettle a Government by Biſhops, pretending to be <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour to the Presbyters, claiming ſole power of Order and Juriſdiction and exerciſing their Juriſdiction by Lay-Chancellors: and if they would not adviſe this, much leſs would they adviſe to ſilence every one that ſhould not aſſent to, and approve of ſuch a Government. If you can think that Mr. <hi>Durells</hi> Teſtimonies prove they would; I beſeech you then make uſe of your Logick, reduce his Teſtimonies into the form of a Syllogiſm, and if the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion follow from every one of his premiſes, or from any one of them, I will then humbly beg your pardon and his too: Indeed ſome of his Teſtimonies are ſuch, as I much doubt, whether he brought them in jeſt, or in earneſt. <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> and <hi>Bogerman</hi> are made to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hierarchy, pag. 252, 268. Becauſe the one did write, the other ſpeak to <hi>Engliſh</hi> Biſhops by thoſe names and titles by which they are commonly notified here in <hi>England.</hi> But is not this to affront us, as if we were quite void of Learning? may we not as well argue from Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi>'s un-Biſhoping of <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> that he alſo appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102358:13"/>
the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hierarchy, becauſe he dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates a Book with that name to the two Arch-Biſhops by the Titles of Right Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in God, Primates and Metropolitanes of all <hi>England:</hi> Is not this to lay a ſtumbling block in the way of the blind Quakers, and to make that ſilly Generation yet more averſe from giving men thoſe names, by which they are dignified in the places where they live? To ſuggeſt that a man cannot call one by the name commonly given him, but he muſt be interpreted to approve his office, and the way of coming to his office, and the claim he makes to his office? But it is alſo ſaid of <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> that he ſubmitted to the Biſhops whilſt he was in <hi>England,</hi> pag. 252. Did he ſo? In what I wonder? Had they any pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over the Kings Profeſſor? Could they ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther viſit him or ſilence him? And what if he had ſubmitted to them? muſt he needs ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to them as to an order of men ſuperior by Divine Law? to that Order of which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was? <hi>Cranmer</hi> moſt familiar with <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr,</hi> never claim'd to be of ſuch an Order, as his Manuſcript kept by Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> will witneſs; much leſs did he deſire <hi>Martyr,</hi> or <hi>Bucer,</hi> or <hi>Fagius,</hi> to be reordain'd by him, that they might be capable of Eccleſiaſtical preferments; ſo as ſubmiſſion then was quite another thing to what it is now. Yet even the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102358:13"/>
Non-Conformiſts of that age thought they had wherewith to juſtifie their Non-Conformity, and to ſpeak as ſoftly as is poſſible, they did as much credit the cauſe of the Proteſtants by ſuffering, as did any of the Conformiſts. And if I might make com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſons, none of them ever recanted for a time, as <hi>Cranmer</hi> did; none of them during the time of impriſonment went to Maſs as <hi>Ridley</hi> had begun to do, and probably had continued ſo to do, had he not been recalled from that abomination, by the Letter of his Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming Friend Mr. <hi>Bradford.</hi> And the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary courage and conſtancy of our Proto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>martyr, <hi>John Rogers,</hi> a very rigid Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt, did greatly animate Biſhop <hi>Ridly,</hi> as he himſelf acknowledges, I pleaſe not my ſelf in theſe compariſons, ſhould not have made them, had not Mr. <hi>Durell</hi>'s pen dropt ſomwhat a foul blot upon the name of Biſhop <hi>Hooper's</hi> friend <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> whom he will needs repreſent to be ſo ſimple, as to ſcruple the Cap, becauſe of its Mathematicalneſs: But he was too wiſe, to ſcruple the Cap on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch account; And hath better deſerved of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, than that he ſhould ſo many years after his death be ſo flouted at, as alſo Biſhop <hi>Hooper</hi> ſhould have had more reverence ſhew'd him, than to be charged as he is pag. 239. with <hi>a ſtrange weakneſs,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:102358:14"/>
for ſticking at our Ceremonies.</p>
            <p>Let us now ſee how well Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> hath acquitted himſelf about forms of Prayer: It muſt be acknowledg'd he hath ſufficiently prov'd from the Teſtimonies of Reformed Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, that forms of Prayer of humane compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition are not unlawful; but the ſame thing had been long ago proved to his hand by a Nonconformiſt Miniſter, Mr. <hi>John Ball</hi> in his Diſcourſe againſt Separation, as alſo by Dr. <hi>John Hoornbek</hi> in his Epiſtle touching Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency: ſo that I cannot wel tel what it was that made Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> ſo copious on this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, unleſs he thought it wiſdom to drive that nail which would go. I do aſſure him, I never yet met with a Presbyterian that thought forms of Prayer unlawful, or that thought it ſimply unlawful for a Church to agree upon forms of Prayer to be uſed by Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in the Publick Congregation. But if he can either prove that it is lawful for the Church to allow her Miniſters no Liberty to uſe their own gifts for Prayer in the Publick, or prove that our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church hath left her Miniſters any ſuch Liberty, then ſhall he do Knight-ſervice.</p>
            <p>In the firſt undertaking, he will have the Presbyterians his adverſaries; In the ſecond, he will have Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> and many others as Canonical as himſelf to cope with. I have
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102358:14"/>
heard a Presbyterian diſputing againſt ſundry Paſſages in the Common-Prayer Book, and wondring why the Convocation ſhould tye all Colledges and Halls to make uſe thereof, without any omiſſion or alteration, when as there is not in the whole Book any one Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the Univerſities, and I was heartily troubled that I had not wherewith to remove my Friends admiration: But had I ever heard him ſay that a Form of Prayer was a breach of the ſecond Commandment, I ſhould have pittied his Ignoranc, as I unfeignedly do the Ignorance of all thoſe who account it any glory to a Reformation to leave in it no helps for ſome Miniſters Infirmities. In this number cannot be placed either the Aſſembly of Divines, or the two Houſes of Parliament that convened them. They both intended the Directory that Miniſters might, if need were, have ſome help and furniture in their Adminiſtrations; and truly it was ſo ſufficient an help and furniture, that he who needed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, could ſcarce be thought worthy to be a ſervant of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in the work of the Miniſtry. Here I muſt be pardon'd, if I reprove the preſumption of Mr. <hi>Durell,</hi> who trembles not pag. 3. to lay to the charge of Lords and Commons, and Aſſembly of Divines, <hi>the delivering of manifest untruths:</hi> The untruths are there ſaid to be,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:102358:15"/>Firſt, <hi>That the Common Prayer Book had prov'd an offence to the Reformed Churches a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That it was aboliſh'd to anſwer the expectations of other Reformed Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay thoſe are no untruths; The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer Book had proved an offence to the Reformed Churches abroad. <hi>Apollonius</hi> hath ſignified ſo much in reference to the <hi>Walachrian</hi> Churches, and others as famous as <hi>Apollonius</hi> have given us to underſtand as much in relation to the Churches of which they were Miniſters; as the Latine Apologiſt hath too plainly proved: and can any one imagine that ſome Ceremonies preſcribed in the Liturgy, were not an offence to <hi>Martyr</hi> and <hi>Zanchy?</hi> Perhaps thoſe learned men did not count them ſimply unlawful, but certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they were offended with them, and wiſht them remov'd: Was it no offence to any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, that ſo many Legends out of the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> were appointed to be read in our Temples? No offence to Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that Infants Baptized were affirmed to to be undoubtedly ſaved? Leſs colour is there to ſay there was a manifeſt untruth in aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Common-Prayer Book was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away to anſwer the expectation of other Reformed Churches; For it is notorious that the Churches of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>New-England,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:102358:15"/>
did expect from the Parliament the abolition of the Liturgy; and certainly, they might with propriety enough be called other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, if none beſides them had expected the ſaid abolition, as we can prove ſome others did: I muſt alſo crave leave to cenſure the Manifeſto of Mr. <hi>Durell,</hi> publiſht with a <hi>Noverint univerſi. Let all the world know that there never was, nor is yet any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Church, that hath onely a Directory and not a Book of Common-Prayer for the publick worſhip of God.</hi> I ask, were there no Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches in the times of the Apoſtles, or men Apoſtolical? I trow there were, Yet it is certain, ſaith <hi>Capellus,</hi> that then there was no Preſcript Form of Liturgy; nor doth that Author give us any notice of any Preſcript Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgies, untill Leaders and Doctors grew idle: were there when his Manifeſto was publiſhed no Reformed Churches in <hi>New-England?</hi> or had theſe Churches Books of Common-Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? and why I ſtrange are Directory and Book of Common-Prayer made oppoſit? were there not in ſome Reformed Churches Books of Common-Prayer, that were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be uſed but as Directories, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing left free to the Miniſters, either to uſe thoſe Printed Prayers, or any other agreeable to them; this freedome I am ſure ſundry emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and worthy Divines in <hi>Holland</hi> have all
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102358:16"/>
along uſed: Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> indeed ſaith, that there is not one Miniſter in all <hi>Franoe</hi> but hath made unto himſelf a ſet Form which he uſeth alwaies, and no other; pag. 18. which is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly a bold aſſertion and ſuppoſeth him to have had conference with every Miniſter in <hi>France,</hi> or to have received Letters from eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, or at leaſt to have employ'd Agents that had made enquiry concerning every one; which if true, would argue him a man of wonderful intelligence: Did never any one Miniſter in all <hi>France,</hi> make unto himſelf above one ſet Form of Prayer. Did, and doth every one of them preciſely keep him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to thoſe very words which he put together when he firſt entred into his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry? Did never any one after God had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored him to his Congregation from ſome e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent ſickneſs, put in any one word to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs his ſenſe of Divine Goodneſs? I will here ſuſpend my belief till I have received ſome farther Information, or can better tell in what ſenſe Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> would have his words taken; for it may be he would have his own Phraſes expounded as he himſelf, pag. 17. expounds ſome Phraſes in one of the <hi>French Rubricks</hi> upon Sundays in the morning, the following Form <hi>is commonly uſed;</hi> The mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whereof he tells us there, is, That it is to be <hi>alway uſed,</hi> and no other: A gloſs that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:102358:16"/>
ſounds marvellous ſtrange to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> ears, which have been accuſtomed to diſtinguiſh betwixt Commonly and Always; and will not eaſily unlearn that diſtinction: and ſo when we hear out of the Harmony of the <hi>Belgick</hi> Synods a Miniſter ſhall pray either by a certain Form propoſed to himſelf, or elſe the Spirit ſhall dictate; we are wont to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that the meaning is not that a Miniſter ſhall never pray but by a Form; it may be Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> is of another mind: if he be, he may do well to communicate to the world the grounds of ſo ſingular an opinion, and when he ſhall ſo do he may do well alſo to give us his thoughts concerning the practice of the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Churches, where it ſeems the Ritual Books or Formula's are delivered onely to the Paſtors, the Reaſon whereof <hi>Comenius</hi> in his Annot. pag. 101. ſaith is, <hi>That the Auditors might be more attent, and more profoundly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the grace of God, for</hi> (ſays he) <hi>if onely preſcribed things are alwaies recited, what is there that may ſtir up attention, Curioſity ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will be ſtirred up whilſt this and the other man attends, whether the Miniſter reads exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſame things which they behold in their own books; nor (addeth he) muſt we think that the Miniſters are tyed to the very words and ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lables of the books delivered to them; it is free according to variety of occaſions to uſe any thing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102358:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
drawn out of the Treaſures of myſtical wiſdome which makes for the exciting of zeal, whence it eomes to paſs that pious Auditors are ſcarcely ever preſent at holy Myſteries without a new motion of heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My imagination on the reading of theſe words is, that <hi>Comenius</hi> was not hugely fond of preſcribed Formula's in which the people were as well verſed as the Miniſter: he ſeems rather to be of opinion, that if words flow from the mouth of the Miniſter which the People had not ſeen before hand, they will be heard with the more Devotion: whether Mr. <hi>Durell's</hi> imaginations agree with mine, time may diſcover; mean while I may have leave to gueſs what it was that moved Mr. <hi>Durell</hi>'s pen to run into ſuch exceſs of riot againſt the two Houſes and Aſſembly, and I conceive it was the extravagance of his Country-man <hi>Ludovicus Capellus</hi> in his diſcourſe about Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgies, unhappily inſerted into the <hi>Theſes Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murienſes;</hi> for his words Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> has punctually tranſcribed and done into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> a Scholler may find them in the third part of thoſe <hi>Theſes,</hi> p. 707.</p>
            <p>I ſhall follow Mr. <hi>Durell's</hi> own Tranſlation pag. 15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>One hundred forty years ago when the ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was made from the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>and that the Chriſtian people coming out of</hi> Babylon,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:102358:17"/>
               <hi>did cast off the Popes Tyranny, the ſacred Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy was purged of all that Popiſh Superſtition and Idolatry, and all ſuch things as were overbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſom, or which did contribute but little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the edification of the Church. And ſo were framed and preſcribed in ſeveral places, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſet forms of holy Liturgies, by the ſeveral Authors of the Reformation that then was; and thoſe ſimple and pure in</hi> Germany, France, England, Scotland, <hi>the</hi> Netherlands, &amp;c. <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering as little as poſſible from the antient ſet Forms of the Primitive Church; which ſet Forms the Reformed have uſed hitherto, with happineſs and profit, each of them in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Nations and diſtricts; till at last of very late, there did ariſe in</hi> England <hi>a froward ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous and over nice (that I ſay not altogether ſuperſtitious) Generation of men, unto whom it hath ſeemed good for many Reaſons, but thoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry light and almoſt of no moment at all, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to blame, but to caſhier and aboliſh wholly the Liturgy uſed hitherto in their Church, together with the whole Hierarchical Government of their Biſhops; inſtead of which Liturgy they have brought in their Directory as they call it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the words thus tranſlated I adventure to ſay.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That I am not much in love with the Profeſſors Chronology; He gratifies the Papiſts too much to ſay, or but to intimate
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:102358:18"/>
that no ſeceſſion was made from their Church till an hundred and forty Years before he put forth thoſe <hi>Theſes,</hi> ſome Churches had gone out of <hi>Babylon</hi> much ſooner, ſome not ſo ſoon.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I am leſs in love with his jum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling together of the Liturgies of <hi>Germany, France, England, Scotland, Belgia,</hi> for if the <hi>Germans</hi> did purge their Liturgie of every thing that was over-burdenſom and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, or which did contribute but little or nothing to the edification of the Church, let a reaſon be given me why we leave any thing out of our Liturgies which they retain? did this Profeſſor of Divinity think that nothing is retained in the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Liturgies that is burdenſom and operoſous or that makes little to edification, or did he conceit that none of the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Churches are <hi>German?</hi> do the <hi>Lutherans</hi> Latine Songs contribute much to edification? are their Images apt to teach the ſoul? did ever any one get much good by having the bread put into his mouth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of having it broken and delivered into his hand? what is I wonder the advantage of Exorciſm? certainly if the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies recede as little as may be from the Forms of the Primitive Church, other Churches have receded very much from them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:102358:18"/>Thirdly, It was a great miſadventure to affirm that the Reformed had with profit and happineſs each of them in their ſeveral Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Diſtricts, uſed ſet Forms till lately the Liturgy was Caſhired in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had not <hi>Calderwood</hi> told the world long ſince, that for many years he had not uſed ſet Forms whilſt he was Miniſter in <hi>Scotland?</hi> was not the Liturgy laid aſide in <hi>Scotland</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, It is a ſign of no great humility, for one Profeſſor ſo ſeverely to cenſure the actings of a whole Aſſembly of Divines, in which were many Superiour to himſelf in Learning; but let not Epiſcopal Divines much glory to find the Aſſemblies Reaſons ſo vilified, they will find the Reaſon of Mr. <hi>Hook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> their Oracle, as much vilified in this Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor's <hi>Theſis de Feſtis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, It is very Probable the good Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor had never read the Directory, <hi>elſe he would not have left it on Record, that the Directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry contains onely the Arguments of things to be ſaid and done in the Adminiſtration of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments;</hi> for in the Directory, the words for Adminiſtration of Baptiſm are preſcribed, ſo are the words for the Adminiſtration of the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> therefore by tranſlating <hi>Capellus</hi> into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> hath but uncovered his naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:102358:19"/>
expoſing him to contempt, who was before become too contemptible, by decrying the Hebrew points and Scripture Chronology, ſo opening a door to down-right infidelity: Yet as if he had not done him ſpight enough, He not only gives us his Text, but alſo draws ſix Obſervations from it, <hi>pag.</hi> 15, 16. in five of which he moſt groſly abuſes him. The firſt is, <hi>That all Reformed Churches have Liturgies:</hi> This I ſay follows not from any words of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellus,</hi> if Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> ſay it doth, his Logick is his own, let him make uſe of it. The ſecond is, <hi>That the Liturgy of the Church of</hi> England <hi>is judged by this great man to be not onely pure and free from all Popiſh Superſtition and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, but alſo from all ſuch things as were onerous and troubleſome, or which did contribute but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to the Edification of the Church, as well as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Reformed Churches.</hi> Twenty Cart-ropes will not pull this obſervation out of <hi>Capellus</hi> his words. He onely ſpeaks of the Liturgy made by the firſt Reformers of our Church, which vaſtly differs from the preſent Liturgy that Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> takes upon him to defend. The third Obſervation is of all moſt marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, thus worded; <hi>If theſe Liturgies ought to recede as little as poſſible from that of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church as he doth intimate, undoubtedly the Liturgy of the Church of</hi> England <hi>is the beſt and moſt perfect of them all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:102358:19"/>If Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> will have this obſerved, we will obſerve it as the iſſue of an over-confident fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, yet humbly praying that he would allow us to think that this obſervation hath no rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the world to any words of <hi>Capellus;</hi> If he may be judge, our Liturgy differs more from the Primitive Liturgies, then the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of any Reformed Churches; for he ſayes, <hi>Primitive Liturgies were moſt brief and moſt ſimple, conſiſting of a few prayers, &amp;c.</hi> Now if we ſhould grant our Liturgy to be very ſimple, certainly it is not very brief, nor does it conſiſt of but a few Prayers: let Mr. <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell</hi> officiate according to it Morning and Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which I never knew any Conformiſt to do, and I will be bold to ſay, his Sermons af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ſhall not be over tedious: The fourth Obſervation is, <hi>That of all who call themſelves Reformed, the Presbyterians are the firſt that ever left off the uſe of ſet Forms of Prayer. Capellus</hi> hath not the word Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians in his work; nor am I certain whom Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> underſtands by them; perhaps he means the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Presbyterians, but how came they to be Presbyterians <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>? <hi>Capellus</hi> was too wiſe a man to ſay, that they were the firſt that left off ſet Forms of Prayer; he knew well enough unleſs he onely was a ſtranger in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that many years before the Aſſembly met at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> ſet Forms of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:102358:20"/>
Prayer had been laid aſide and condemned as unlawful, by huge multitudes who were angry with the old meer Nonconformiſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would not ſeperate from the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, as well as endeavour a Reformation of ſome things. The fifth Obſervation is, <hi>That the many reaſons for which the Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans had rejected the Common-Prayer Book, are very light, and almoſt of no moment at all:</hi> 'Tis true that <hi>Capellus</hi> hath written ſomething to this purpoſe, but it is the ſame <hi>Capellus</hi> who hath written ſo many bug-bear words againſt our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Biſhops, in his <hi>Theſes de deſcrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Epiſcopi &amp; Presbyteri, &amp; de vario Eccleſiae regimine,</hi> the former <hi>Theſes</hi> he concludes thus, <hi>That there was no cauſe why the Biſhops and their Patrons ſhould ſo greatly inſult, and onely not grow inſolent againſt thoſe whom invidiouſly they called Puritans and Presbyterians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let it be obſerved; that if the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians had onely reproved, and not caſhier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Common-Prayer Book, their Reaſons might have been ſufficient, notwithſtanding any thing <hi>Capellus</hi> ſaith to the contrary. Sixth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> would have it obſerved, <hi>That the Presbyterians themſelves who are the known Authors of the Directory, are in</hi> Capellus <hi>his Judgment a froward, peeviſh and ſuperſtitous Generation of men. Capellus</hi> does indeed call the Compoſers of the Directory moroſe and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:102358:20"/>
froward, but ſeems unwilling to call them ſuperſtitious; and the ſame <hi>Capellus</hi> had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended them for ſhaking off the Yoke of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy in his <hi>Theſes de Vario Eccleſiae regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> Sect. 24. Let Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> when he puts out next, <hi>Engliſh</hi> theſe words, for they ſeem framed according to the Heart of the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians, and let him then alſo tell us, why he calls the Presbyterians <hi>the known Authors of the Directory.</hi> That Aſſembly that preſented the Directory to the two Houſes, was as to moſt of its Members, when firſt called, Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchical, and under an Oath of Canonical o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience; there are not very many of them living at preſent; of them diverſe conform, and are as deeply engaged to uſe Liturgical worſhip as Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> himſelf; let him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when he has opportunity, enquire of them, whether they conſented to have the Liturgy caſhiered? and how they came to fall in love with it again? and what made them ſo fearful leaſt the old ſubſcription ſhould choak us, when as they themſelves can ſwallow theſe new ones that are far bigger and more bulky?</p>
            <p>By this time I hope it is come to my turn to make ſome obſervations upon the <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> of <hi>Capellus,</hi> and my Obſervations may be the fewer becauſe I have already ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo many, and the firſt thing I obſerve is,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:102358:21"/>
That the men againſt whom <hi>Capellus</hi> was ſo not, could not be the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Presbyterians, unleſs they were falſly repreſented to him: for theſe are his words, pag. 710, 711. <hi>They with whom we have to do, bewray a manifeſt enough hatred againſt Formula's of Symbols or Confeſſions of Faith, and of Catechiſm, and the both antient and recent uſe and cuſtome of them received in the Chriſtian Church.</hi> If theſe are the men he had to deal with, then had he nothing to do with the Engliſh Presbyterians, no men having more contended for Confeſſions of Faith and Catechiſms in ſet words than they. Secondly, I obſerve that he repreſents himſelf and his fellow Profeſſors as not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning or inhibiting a free uſe of Prayers compoſed by Miniſters themſelves. Nay theſe are his words, pag. 713. <hi>We plainly think it both lawful and conſentaneous that they who can do it, ſhould diſcover their gift and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry in praying, as in preaching, this onely we will, that the uſe of ſuch prayers ought not to hinder the Liturgy conſtituted by publick Authority, and to take away and abrogate all uſe of it out of the Church.</hi> And a little after he adds. <hi>We de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly condemn the rigour of thoſe, who under pretext of a praeſcript Form of Liturgy, do ſtudy to eliminate out of the Church all uſe of Prayers conceived by Miniſters themſelves.</hi> Let Mr. <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell</hi> conſider, whether this Damnatory ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:102358:21"/>
do not fall upon many of his own Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons and Abettours. Thirdly, I obſerve that when the Profeſſor comes to contract what he had ſaid, he determines concerning Formu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la's, as if <hi>Smectymnuus</hi> had too much influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him, for he ſaith firſt, <hi>That they are not abſolutely in every time and place, and with all men neceſſary, becauſe the Chriſtian Church want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them for ſome time; and it does not appear from ſacred or exotick Hiſtory, whether the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Church did not want them before Chriſt, and</hi> Ezra, <hi>and from the time of</hi> Moſes. Secondly, <hi>That they are not commonly neceſſary but for or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Decorum.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Where and when there cannot be had learned Paſtours who are able to teach, the people by their Sermons and proper Prayers, that there Formula's are plainly neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> Fourthly, <hi>Where there are learned and skilful Paſtors, a publick Form of Liturgy is very profitable, and neceſſary to the Common E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification of the Church in the ſame Communion of Divine worſhip.</hi> Fifthly, <hi>That the uſe of ſuch Forms cannot juſtly be condemned or diſaproved, nor ought it, ſeeing it may be alwaies and every where profitable and most convenient, and has obtained in the whole Chriſtian Church all the world over, for above</hi> 1300 <hi>years, and does eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where now obtain, but with thoſe Independant Novices.</hi> Let Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> after this, take heed how he commends Liturgies, by the pen of his
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:102358:22"/>
moſt applauded forreign Divines: and let him know, that all the pains he takes, to make the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Liturgies the ſame, or near a kin with and to ours, doth indeed tend to the reproach of Archbiſhop <hi>Laud.</hi> For if there were no difference, or but ſmall betwixt them, why was he ſo zealous as his <hi>Historian</hi> repreſents him, in proſecuting and preſſing the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Churches, to have our Liturgy tranſlated into their Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and uſed by them in all their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches granted them in <hi>England?</hi> however, let me warn Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> to take heed, that he do not go on with that deſigne he hath ſo oft ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted us with, I mean the deſign of Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together the Formula's and Agenda's of all the Reformed Churches in Chriſtendome: for though this deſign might perhaps pleaſe himſelf (as who is not pleaſed with the iſſue of his own Brain) yet I much queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it would be any way pleaſing to the moſt Reverend and Right Reverend Prelates of our Church. Certain I am, that it is not many years, ſince ſome of our greateſt Eccleſiaſticks plainly enough declared, that ſuch a deſigne would not much relliſh with them, for when the Prince Elector Palatine came over to viſit his Unckle, King <hi>Charles</hi> I. in <hi>England,</hi> which was about 34 years ago, ſome buſie heads (as Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> calls them) publiſhed
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:102358:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
a book intituled, <hi>A Declaration of the Faith and Ceremonies of the Palſgraves Churches.</hi> What was the effect of the Publication? a courſe was forthwith taken to call it in <hi>for the ſame cauſe, and on the ſame prudential grounds</hi> (adds Dr. <hi>Heylin) on which the alteration</hi> (I before mentioned) <hi>was made in the Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents.</hi> But I needed not ſo long to have inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon Liturgies, having before told you what he muſt do that hopes to bring the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt to ſubſcription; he muſt prove that the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath left Miniſters any power to make uſe of their gifts in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, for if that be not proved, they will ſhrewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly argue againſt the lawfulneſs of promiſes to bury their gift in a napkin, but whether this be proved or no, the Nonconformiſts that I ſpeak with, will be but Nonconformiſts; not forſaking the publick Aſſemblies, but rejoyce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to hear Chriſt Preached, though not without ſome bitter reflections upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>I come to Ceremonies, and the firſt of them that occurres, is the Surplice, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which, my Nonconformiſts Friends ſay, That if they uſed it as enjoyned by the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, they muſt receive it; <hi>as a veſtment apt by ſome notable ſignification it hath, to ſtir up the dull mind;</hi> Now that I might ſatisfie their Scruple, I have gone to ſome Conformiſts and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:102358:23"/>
enquired of them, whether ever they experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented any ſuch aptneſs in it to ſtir up their dull minds; they moſt of them wondred at my Queſtion, telling me that by aſſenting and conſenting, they meant no more but onely to promiſe, that they would not openly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict any thing in the Liturgy; you may eaſily imagine what motion this reply ſtirred up in my dull mind; onely one anſwered, that though he would not boaſt of his own expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riences, yet he doubted not but the holy Veſtment had a fitneſs in it to ſtir up the dull mind; but I asking him further, whether it was apt to ſtir him up <hi>as a man,</hi> or <hi>as an Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh man?</hi> he gave me to underſtand that he was not willing to be preſſed further. I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted my ſelf however in this, that Mr. <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell</hi> would tell me ſome ſtories, of ſome great livelineſs put into men by the wearing of the white Garment, but he quite deceived me, onely giving me to underſtand, pag. 24, 25. <hi>Of ſome of other Reformed Churches that to comply with the Lutherans, do ſomtimes wear Surplices.</hi> This is but cold kindneſs, and that I may not be in debt to him for it, I give him to underſtand, <hi>That no Lutherans in the Low Countries do wear Surplices;</hi> and they forbear to wear them, not becauſe the Magiſtrate would not give them leave to wear them, but becauſe they want a will to wear them, which
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:102358:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
makes me think that they have no high opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion concerning the uſefulneſs of them; nor can I think that our own Miniſters have any huge apprehenſions of this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing vertue of the Surplice, for whereas they are enjoined to wear it as oft as they officiate; I find few of them ſo to do, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them never wear it, but when a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is to be Adminiſtred. Perhaps I ſhall be able to afford my Nonconformiſts more help and aſſiſtance againſt his Scruples a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Croſs in Baptiſme: His Scruples are founded upon this bottom; That the Croſs is made aſign of the Childs Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to God, and alſo a ſign of his perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in Grace, and ſuch a ſign they ſay is Sacramental, which kind of ſign the Church has no Commiſſion from God to inſtitute; I have taken ſome pains that I might be able from the writings of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts to aſſoile this Objection. Mr. <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell</hi> tells us, <hi>Serm. pag.</hi> 29. <hi>That the Croſs is indeed a viſible ſign, but there is no inviſible Grace anſwering to it; and ſo no Sacrament.</hi> I could not acquieſce in this, for I thought <hi>Dedication to God, and Perſeverance</hi> were graces; and if they be Graces, I am ſure they are inviſible Graces; I have alſo ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times wondred, ſeeing Baptiſm it ſelf was inſtituted as a Dedicating ſign, and ſeeing
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:102358:24"/>
by it we engage our ſelves to perſeverance, and God alſo engages to give unto Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers the Grace of Perſeverance; what might move our Church to inſtitute the Croſs as a new ſign of any of theſe things? eſpecially ſeeing yet I never had the hap to meet with any who could from their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience averre unto me that the ſign of the Croſs with which they were ſigned at Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, had added to them any degree of manfulneſs: nor by comparing ſeveral Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized perſons could I ever obſerve, that perſons Croſſed at Baptiſme, were leſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to be aſhamed of Chriſt Crucified, than thoſe that were Baptized, not being Croſſed. Indeed this ſign of the Croſs hath Miniſtred more matter of Scruple to the Nonconformiſts, then any other Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny beſides; and therefore Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> ſhould not have dealt ſlightly in this matter, which yet any one may obſerve that he does, for inſtead of giving us inſtances of Reformed Churches that uſe the Croſs in Baptiſme. He contents himſelf to give us a few in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Reformed Churches, that uſe the Croſs out of Baptiſme; the Church of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva,</hi> he ſaies, <hi>Makes the Chriſtian Religion in a picture, to lean upon the Croſs,</hi> page 21. and page 31. <hi>Does not think the Chriſtian Religion ſufficiently repreſented without the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:102358:24"/>
of a Croſs.</hi> And the French Churches agreed Anno 1609. <hi>That they would not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barre from the Sacrament, ſuch as ſhould wear Croſſes upon their Cloaks; in caſe the King would not allow them the maintenance for maimed ſouldiers untill they did wear ſuch Croſſes;</hi> He might alſo have added that the Erectors of the ſhort lived Commonwealth among us, did appoint a Croſs to be ſet upon that Money which they preſumed to Coin, and alſo put the figure of a Croſs into the Flags of thoſe ſhips which they ſet forth againſt his Sacred Majeſty; and had he ſo done, would not any one at laſt have asked him to what purpoſe is all this waſte of Examples? never did ſober Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian or Independant queſtion ſuch kind of Croſſes, many of them perhaps will be found to have them in their Coat of Arms, and in their Signets with which they uſe to Seal their Letters; and yet would at no hand be induced to ſuffer their Children to be Baptized with the ſign of the Croſs, as a <hi>ſigne of their Dedication to God, or as a token that afterwards they ſhould not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of Chriſt Crucified, &amp;c.</hi> Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> had ſure forgot that the Croſs our Church ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points is a Tranſient Croſs (by which Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> would have it diſtinguiſhed ſufficiently from the Croſs of the Papiſts
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:102358:25"/>
which is permanent) elſe he would not have brought ſo many inſtances of perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Croſſes which being the Objects of ſight, may occaſion in us ſome good thoughts and meditations concerning the Croſs on which our Lord Jeſus did ſuffer, but the Tranſient Croſs leaving no viſible impreſſion on us, has no ſuch aptneſs objectively to ſtir in us any good thought concerning Chriſt Crucified, and it is hard to conceive how it ſhould be uſeful in the way of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, unleſs we had ſome one to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh us that we were Croſſed with ſuch a Croſs: I know that dipping, or ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Water, upon the body, leaves no viſible impreſſion upon it neither, but the ſpirit who alwaies abides in believers, hath an office to bring baptiſm to their remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and hath ſo effectually brought it to remembrance that they have from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations drawn from it, quenched the fiery darts of Satan, that this bleſſed Spirit will concern himſelf to bring our being Croſſed in Baptiſme to remembrance Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> will not haſtily affirm: what then? would Presbyterians better approve of the making of a permanent Croſs on the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of newly Baptiſed Infants? ſurely no. But they ſometimes argue thus, <hi>ad homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem,</hi> and think that their is ſtrength in
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:102358:25"/>
their arguings. Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> hath no where that I can find, ſhewed their ſtrength to be but weakneſs; rather he hath ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their hands by ſome expreſſions uſed in his Sermon, pag. 23. <hi>Where he placeth Chriſm uſed in Confirmation amongſt ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious or ſuperfluous Ceremonies:</hi> Now why the Chriſm in Confirmation ſhould be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuperſtitious or ſuperfluous, and the Croſs in Baptiſme not be ſo accounted, there can no good reaſon at all be aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Is the Croſs antient, ſo is Chriſme; the Croſs as much abuſed by the Papiſts, as ever was the Chriſm: the Croſs made ſignificant of what Baptiſme it ſelf ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and ſignified more clearly than the Croſs can ſignifie: and therefore ſuperfluous enough, if that be ſuperfluous which is uſed for the doing of that which was ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done before; whereas in Confirmation there is no outward viſible ſign to ſignifie that which Chriſm ſignifies; <hi>viz.</hi> Anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Holy Ghoſt inwardly, as may be collected from a Petition yet retained in the Liturgy for Confirmation.</p>
            <p>I am not now at leiſure to enquire ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the uſuages of Reformed Churches abroad, nor into the Sentiments of their Divines concerning our Ceremonies; but this I have found, that thoſe who have
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:102358:26"/>
gone from our Univerſities and travelled into forreign Reformed Churches, and Kingdomes, have generally returned to us again with very little fondneſs for our Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies; now it ſeems very ſtrange, that if the ſame Ceremonies be uſed abroad, that are uſed here, or if they abroad count them as indifferent as we do them at home, that Travells ſhould ingenerate in any a diſlike of them: and it is ſtrange alſo if Mr. <hi>Beza</hi> had no worſe thoughts of out Diſcipline and Rights, then Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> would make ſhew of; that he ſhould have ſo good thoughts of Mr. <hi>Travers,</hi> and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other chief Nonconformiſts in <hi>England,</hi> as to make them his greateſt Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents; for ſo I can prove he did by Letters ſtill extant.</p>
            <p>Hitherto I have ſhewed you, how much Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> hath miſtaken, and miſ-repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the ſtate of thoſe Controverſies that are on foot among us; I will now give you in a ſhort Catalogue of Impertinences, by which you ſhall ſee that he hath ſtuff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Book with Teſtimonies, to prove that which never any Presbyterian deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or ever gave him the leaſt occaſion to think he denyed; The firſt place in this Catalogue is due to his Teſtimonies muſtered up, pag. 51, 52. relating to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:102358:26"/>
a Species whereof he ſaies is the purchaſing and detaining of Church Lands: I for my part think ſo too, and never yet met with a Presbyterian that thought otherwiſe: if there be a true ſuperfluity of Church Lands, then the Magiſtrate doubtleſs may out of that ſuperfluity take for any other good uſe, though it be not directly Eccleſiaſtical. In ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes alſo of great neceſſity Church Lands ſeem not to be priviledged from ſale; nor can any wiſe man doubt but that it is the Magiſtrates duty to convert ſuch Lands as were given to the Church by a Zeale without knowledge, and to promote Idolatry and Superſtition, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch uſes as are truly pious and acceptable unto God. Theſe, and other ſuch like Caſes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, the Presbyterians would as willingly have a <hi>Noli me tangere</hi> upon every parcel of the Church Lands as Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> himſelf. He tells us indeed, page 51. <hi>That many here among us and ſome of them Presbyterian Miniſters made nothing of purchaſing and detaining Church Lands;</hi> and another, as very a Scribler as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, hath told us, <hi>That in the Annotations com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly known by the name of the Aſſemblies Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations he could never meet with any thing againſt Sacriledge in any of thoſe places where he had conſulted them;</hi> the firſt edition of thoſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notations I have not by me, but if that Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had nothing in it againſt Sacriledge, let
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:102358:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the Saddle be ſet upon the right Horſe, and the blame laid upon Dr. <hi>Daniel Feately,</hi> who Commenting upon <hi>Romans</hi> the 2d. where the word Sacriledge occurs, would let it paſs uncenſured; but I have heard that in our latter Editions of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notations Dr. <hi>Feateleys</hi> Notes are not altered; if ſo, the Debator hath reaſon to be aſhamed of his impudence, and railing accuſation, for any one may ſee that Sacriledge is ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condemned at <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.22. and it is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely Cenſured <hi>Acts</hi> 5. as alſo <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.25. and if that be not alſo cenſured <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 48. who muſt bear the blame, but Biſhop <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardſon</hi> to whoſe ſhare it fell to Comment on that portion of Scripture: Certainly the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and third Editions of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations were Printed in times in which it was all out as dangerous to reprove Sacriledge, as in thoſe times in which the firſt Edition was put forth. In thoſe Editions I have already referred to enough that makes againſt Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, yet if need were, I could referr to much more, and poſſibly ſhould ſo do, were it not that the work had been long ſince done to my hand by an Epiſcopal Divine, in a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe Printed 1648. with this Title, <hi>Church Lands not to be ſold.</hi> He that will be at pains to peruſe that book, ſhall ſoon find that no one could keep the Covenant and not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:102358:27"/>
the alienating of Church Lands, <hi>page</hi> 27. he quotes theſe words from Mr. <hi>Gearee</hi> an holy Nonconformiſt: <hi>To aboliſh Prelacy, and to ſeize the Lands of Prelates to private, or civil Intereſt, undoubtedly could neither want ſtain nor guilt;</hi> adding, <hi>I am confident, by the diſcourſe I have had with the moſt able of the Aſſembly of Divines at</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>that at the leaſt three parts, if not all of them are of the ſame Judgment with Mr.</hi> Gearee, <hi>and that they would openly profeſs as much if they were put to anſwer the Queſtion.</hi> But ſaith Mr. <hi>Durell,</hi> ſome of the many who made nothing of purchaſing and detaining Church Lands, <hi>were Presbyterian Miniſters,</hi> and to prove this, <hi>in the Margent he puts Dr.</hi> Burgeſs never ſo much as adding an <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo that in his Arithmetick Dr. <hi>Burgeſs</hi> is ſome Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Miniſters. But he ſhould firſt have proved that he was one Presbyterian Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter before he had gone about to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us that he was ſundry Presbyterian Miniſters. He is not that Dr. <hi>Burgeſs</hi> who defended the three Ceremonies againſt Dr. <hi>Ames,</hi> but yet he is the Dr. <hi>Burgeſs</hi> that took care to have that Defence Printed, and beautified the Margent of it to make it he more pleaſing to the Readers eye; and he is the Dr. <hi>Burgeſs</hi> that did write for Baptiſmal Regeneration, which the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:102358:28"/>
Presbyterian can by no means ſwallow. I have heard indeed that he took the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, but not till he ſaw that it was dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous not to take it. I have heard alſo that he was employed to make a Speech in anſwer to Dr. <hi>John Hackett,</hi> who was to plead for the continuance of Deanes and Chapiters, but in that Speech he openly declared <hi>the utter unlawfulneſs of converting Dean and Chapiters Lands to any private perſons profit:</hi> ſo that he then delivered the ſame Doctrine with Dr. <hi>Hackett,</hi> only differing in the Application, as Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi> words it, book 11. page 179. It ſeems af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards he himſelf was a Purchaſer, and a great Purchaſer contrary to the Doctrine delivered by him, for which I leave him to his own Maſter, unto whom he hath ſome years ſince given his Accounts. Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> as if he were a Privy-Councellor in Heaven, preſumes in his Latin book to ſay, <hi>That the Cancer of which he dyed, befel him for his Sacriledge;</hi> I dare not ſo ſay, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences of God are too great a deep for any man to venture himſelf into, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> might have been deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from ſuch preſumption, by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Gods dealing with Biſhop <hi>Gawden,</hi> who after that he had written for the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, and againſt Sacriledge, dyed not
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:102358:28"/>
long after of a Diſeaſe as loathſome, and far more painful than that which brought Dr. <hi>Burgeſs</hi> to his Grave, and this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe was that very Diſeaſe unto which he had compared the Presbyterian Sermons, and befell him in a very ſhort time after he had made the Compariſon; yet all theſe Circumſtances notwithſtanding no man ſhall ever hear me ſay <hi>That the ſickneſs was a ſtroak of Divine Juſtice inflicted on him for his fierceneſs againſt the Presbyterians.</hi> Indeed the Providence of God is to us ſo hidden and ſecret, that there is no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding from it either love or hatred: and therefore the Sons of the Church have no reaſon to thank Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> for ſaying, page 17. of his Sermon, <hi>That the wonderful man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of raiſing our Church up again is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident proof that ſhe is her Beloveds, and her Beloved hers, and an Argument that her Reformation (ſince neither mens Craft nor violence which ſo far prevailed againſt it were never able to destroy it) is certainly the work of God and his Counſel which ſhall stand. Non tali auxilio, nec defenſoribus istis.</hi> Our Church needs no ſuch Tophicks, ſhe will think that he has a minde to betray her, who uſeth them on her behalf, for who knows how ſoon God provoked by our ſins, may turn the ſtream of his Providences, and bring
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:102358:29"/>
our Church Governours under as great po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty and reproach as ever: If the ſtream of Providence ſhould never turn, yet all Theological ears will abhor to hear our <hi>Engliſh Reformation</hi> called <hi>the Counſell of the Lord which ſhall ſtand.</hi> That is a Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Phraſe and Printed as ſuch by Mr. <hi>Durell,</hi> and therefore ought not to have been ſo palpably wreſted by him: Dare any man think that the Decrees and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of God are changed, unleſs our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation as attended with all its Rites, and Cermonies, endure from generation to generation? But I have almoſt run away from the buſineſs of Sacriledge. If any man deſire to know how zealous Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Divines have been againſt this ſin, he may quickly inform himſelf from Dr. <hi>Hornebeckes Examen bullae Papalis.</hi> I only adde, that ſome men have been ſo har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as to to ſay that our Impropriations are a kind of Sacrilege. The Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> ſeems to be of that mind, and charges all the Parliaments ſince the 31. of <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. with debarring Chriſts Wife of a great part of her dowry: if ſo, Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> may find more Sacriledge among his friends then he is aware of, and he may do well to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire whether the impropriations of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Cathedrals, to which he himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:102358:29"/>
are ſo diſpoſed of, as that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbants reſiding upon them have a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and honerable maintenance allowed them. His Majeſty hath graciouſly emit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Letter, that it might be ſo; if the Letter have been univerſally obeyed, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the obedience given to it, but I am ſure heretofore no Impropriators allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed leſs then Clergy-men; no pariſhes were worſe ſupplied, than thoſe in which the Titles went to the Cathedralls, unleſs Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> be ſure that he and his Fraternities be free from this ſin, it will not be ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for him to throw ſtones at other ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, leaſt it ſhould be ſaid, <hi>thou Hypocrite, firſt, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Second of Mr. <hi>Durell's</hi> Impertinencies, is his Quotation, pag. 40. of the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Churches, <hi>for the peoples ſaying Amen at theend of Prayers.</hi> Did the Presbyterians ever ſay, the People might not ſay Amen at the end of Prayers? are they not rather judged by their Adverſaries, to erre by affirming, that it were meet for the people to ſay nothing elſe but <hi>Amen?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, What made him, pag. 43. <hi>Waſte paper to prove that Confirmation is uſed in moſt Reformed Churches?</hi> Did not Mr. <hi>Hanmer,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> write whole books in the commendation of Confirmation?
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:102358:30"/>
Did the Presbyterians ever more heartily deſire any thing, than that adult perſons might before they were admitted to the Lords Supper, he ordered to make a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith, and to declare their Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution to own that Faith, and to walk ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to it? Did they not alway with grief of heart complain that Confirmation had never been practiſed here in <hi>England,</hi> or elſe had been turned into a meer form?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Wherefore are we told <hi>page</hi> 37, 38. <hi>That the Lords Prayer and Ten Commandments and Creeds, are ſung in ſome Reformed Churches; as alſo the Magnificat, the Benedictus,</hi> and <hi>the Nunc dimittis.</hi> Do the Presbyterians queſtion the lawfulneſs of ſinging any of theſe? or do they require any more than that they ſhould be put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Meeter, and ſet into ſuch tunes as ordinary people might follow? I my ſelf have heare an eminent Presbyterian Divine on a day of Humiliation, read and ſing the Lords Prayer, as it is Tranſlated and Printed at the end of our Pſalm books. Yea, where as Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> tells us <hi>That the</hi> French <hi>Church does not ſing the Lords Prayer, and the Creed of the Apoſtles, becauſe both the Rhyme and Language were ſomthing courſe and old.</hi> Presbyterians never left off to ſing accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:102358:30"/>
to the Vulgar Tranſlation, its oldneſs and courſneſs notwithſtanding, and if hymns ſhould be made out of other places of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture by men wiſe and skilful, who is there that would blame them?</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Who ever quarrelled with the French Churches, <hi>for having great ſilver Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lices for the Communion,</hi> as he tells us they have, pag. 32.</p>
            <p>Or who would be offended if richer Churches had the ten Commandments in Letters of Gold, and the Creed, and the Lords Prayer in the ſame form. I have heard one of the chief Presbyterian Miniſters did rejoice, that the Lords Prayer was by the Painter drawn in very viſible Characters up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a wall, juſt over againſt his Pulpit, for by that means, if at any time he happened to be as much out in repeating of that form; as Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> lately was in the repeating of the Belief, he might help himſelf, and not put himſelf and others to ſhame, as Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> did.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, He tells us pag. 32. <hi>That in all Reformed Churches men uſed to enter into the place of publick worſhip with their hats off,</hi> which is as great an untruth, as ever drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped from writers pen, unleſs it be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of places of publick worſhip, whilſt publick worſhip is actually performed in
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:102358:31"/>
them, and if it may be ſo underſtood, then the Presbyterians would hugely approve of it. By the Directory it was enjoined that, all enter the Aſſembly not irreverently, but in a grave and ſeemly manner: gravity and ſeemlineſs do include putting off the hat, which yet would be a ridiculous action, if a man ſhould uſe it, as too many now a days do as oft as they go through the Church, though none be met for worſhip, and though they themſelves intended no wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: nor does the Directory any where condemn the manner which Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> tells us hath obtained among the French Ladies, <hi>viz. to unmask themſelves when they come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Temple;</hi> provided they do not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mask themſelves out of a vain or wanton deſign; if they ſhould do ſo, they know by whom they are condemned. [<hi>I but ſaith Mr.</hi> Durell, <hi>the devouteſt ſort both of men and women, uſe to kneel and make a Prayer for Gods bleſſing, before they ſit down, and this the Directory prohibites.</hi>] Had he ſaid that the devouter ſort uſe a ſhort Prayer when they took no ſeats, and came to perform no ſervice to God; then he had ſaid ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to excuſe the actings of ſome among us. The peoples making a ſecret Prayer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſit down in their ſeats, is not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by the Directory, unto all, or unto
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:102358:31"/>
any, but theſe who come into the Church the publick worſhip being begun, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be more meet for ſuch to betake themſelves to their private devotions, or to join with the Aſſembly in that ordinance that is in hand, let the learned judge for they are wiſe.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, All might have been ſpared that is brought, pag. 33. Of Peoples ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bare in time of Divine Service, and at the Adminiſtration of Sacraments: In the very Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> all are uncovered at the Adminiſtration of the Sacraments; here in <hi>England</hi> men had left off to put on their hats in time of Sermon (which Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> ſeems to diſtinguiſh from Service) had Mr. <hi>Calamy</hi> and others been hearken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to.</p>
            <p>Eighthly, Above all, what need we be told, pag. 22. <hi>That Calvin wore a Gown and a Cap:</hi> Were not Presbyterians accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed ſo to do in the Univerſities? Thoſe ſent down by the two Houſes to <hi>Cambridge,</hi> did all of them preach in the Univerſity Church in their Gowns, and in their Hoods; and I never heard of any, but Browniſts, that queſtioned the uſing of the very ſame Churches that the Papiſts had uſed; yet we have fine ſtories of that, pag. 28. As alſo of the Ring in Marriage, as if there were ſome
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:102358:32"/>
odde Nonconformiſts that did ſcruple being Married with a Ring. He tells us alſo of Matrimony in the publick Congregation, pag. 47. celebrated alſo by a Miniſter juſt according as the Directory orders; but if he would have gratified us here in <hi>England,</hi> he ſhould have told us that all Reformed Churches do count Marriages valid, though made without and againſt the conſent of Parents, as alſo that they have Officers, whom they allow to give Licenſes for Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, though there have been no Banes publiſhed, nor any thing equivolent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, but to affirm this had been ſomewhat too groſs. Pag. 48, and 49. He minds us, <hi>that in moſt Reformed Churches the dead are buried with great ſolemnity, ſinging of Pſalms, and Funeral Sermons;</hi> as if Presbyterians had ſcrupled the Preaching of Funeral Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, or had not been wont when deſired to Preach them. I believe if Compariſon were made, Presbyterians formerly preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more Funeral Sermons, then Prelatical men do now, and that very many of thoſe for whom Sermons are now Preached, are addicted to Presbytery. Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> ſhould have called to remembrance, that our Church hath appointed no Funeral Sermons, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired any more of her Miniſters, ſave on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to meet the Corps at the Church Stile,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:102358:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and ſo go either into the Church, or to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Grave, to ſay or ſing ſome ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicles out of Holy Writ: I do not find that by the old Liturgy it was required that the Corps ſhould be brought into the Church, though now I find one or two Pſalms ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be read after the Miniſter and people are come into the Church, and by Comparing the old and new Liturgy toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I find where in the old was the word <hi>[Miniſter]</hi> in the new there is conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the word <hi>[Prieſt,]</hi> ſo that whereas a Deacon may preach to us, and Baptize our Children, he may not bury our dead, which ſeems to be a Myſtery worthy Mr. <hi>Durells</hi> unridling. Our Clergy men themſelves ſeem Strangers to this myſtery, for nothing is more uſual among them, than to ſet Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons to bury their dead; nor can I in that old Liturgy which I follow, find any notice given, that the office for the burial of the dead, is not to be uſed at the burial of ſuch as die unbaptized, in the new Liturgy ſuch notice is given; the reaſon whereof I am not ſo happy at preſent as to know: why ſhould Infants that die unbaptized, through no fault of their Parents, be denied ſuch a burial as Baptized Infants have? Mr. <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell</hi> is a knowing man, and can ſatisfie us about theſe matters, and brings us, no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:102358:33"/>
many Reformed Churches where the ſame uſage obtains; but why did he bring in his Friend, Mr. <hi>Drelincourt,</hi> ſaying pag. 49. <hi>That he ſhould account the Cuſtome of the Miniſters of the Reformed Churches in France, being ſilent at dead mens burial, unſufferable, were it not for their preſent condition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That learned worthy Divine knows, that the Reformed Churches in <hi>Holland,</hi> are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der no ſuch condition as the French Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and yet their Miniſters are perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſilent at the burials of dead men; Is their Cuſtome unſufferable? I believe he will not ſo pronounce, and therefore will ſcarce think himſelf civilly dealt with, to have a Fragment of a private Epiſtle thus publiſhed, eſpecially ſeeing it reflects diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace upon the Miniſters of his own nation, who are Paſtors in <hi>Holland;</hi> I have been too tedious in examining this impertinence. The Communion alſo he tells us, pag. 44. <hi>Is conſtantly celebrated at certain ſet times in all Reformed Churches.</hi> And is there any thing in the Directory againſt the celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of it at certain ſet times? Does it not ſay, that it is frequently to be celebrated? And take order that notice ſhall be given be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hand of its celebration? nor does the Directory any where forbid the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring of the Communion unto thoſe that
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:102358:33"/>
are ſick in private houſes, though if it had ſo done, it might have juſtified it ſelf by the Example of many of the beſt Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches. Let Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> when he is at leiſure, enquire whether one of the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of Divines did not Adminiſter the Sacrament to Captain <hi>Hotham</hi> when he was juſt going to be Beheaded? or whether he was ever cenſured for ſo doing?</p>
            <p>I will enlarge my Catalogue no farther; by the inſtances already produced, it appears, that Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> may well be called Mr. <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent.</hi> But I ſhall now by ſundry inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces make it evident alſo, that he hath thruſt ſundry things into his book, that are like e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, if they fall into the hands of a weak Reader, to be prejudicial and pernicious, and to alienate him from our Church. He tells us <hi>page</hi> 8. the <hi>Hungarian</hi> and <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilvanian</hi> Churches are as Pure and Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as any whatſoever; but <hi>page</hi> 10, &amp; 11. he ſpoils all, and takes a great deal of pains ſo to do, borrowing a book very rare and ſcarce; and out of it acquainting us, <hi>That in thoſe Churches Miniſters ſwear obedience Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical unto Presbyters as well as Biſhops:</hi> and, <hi>That Miniſters are to be governed by certain Laws by an eminent ſort of Presbyters, called Elders, as well as by Biſhops.</hi> Then which, what can be more derogatory to the Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:102358:34"/>
Power, Place, Juriiſdiction, and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in Presbyters as well as Biſhops? and what Eminence will there then be left for Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops? what will there be left to a Biſhop, more than what the Presbyterians have a thouſand times over acknowledged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ready to yield him? It may be he thought he ſhould heal his wound by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as he does, <hi>page</hi> 8. <hi>That theſe Elders are indeed Biſhops, and the Biſhops Archbiſhops.</hi> But I ſay they are indeed but a more Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſort of Presbyters; ſo they are expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called, and they can be no other; becauſe they were never by Ordination put into an Office, or Order ſuperior to that of Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; and obſervable it is <hi>(vid. pag. praedict.) That the Miniſter acknowledgeth himſelf in his Oath, to receive the function of the ſacred Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry from the there preſent Miniſters of God, and moſt Faithful diſpenſers of his Myſteries.</hi> Which are Phraſes agreeing unto all that are entruſted with the word of Reconciliation: So that this Teſtimony looks with a very e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil eye upon Epiſcopacy: and ſo does much more the Teſtimony of the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, related <hi>pag.</hi> 11, 12, 13. for in that we have Presbyters Ordaining <hi>Bohemian</hi> Biſhops, a thing that ſounds dreadful to an Epiſcopal ear. This ſtory will ſtrengthen the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians, and be a ſecond unto that with which
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:102358:34"/>
they are wont ſo much to confirme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; I mean the Hiſtory of <hi>Pelagius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> being ordained by two Biſhops and one Presbyter. Theſe Hiſtories do at leaſt prove that Presbyters and Biſhops were of the ſame Order, and that Presbyters as well as Biſhops, may lay hands upon Biſhops, and confer the power of making Miniſters. Indeed the man makes himſelf ridiculous who goes about to look for any Biſhop pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſo called among the <hi>Waldenſes;</hi> and he does gratifie the Presbyterians not a little, <hi>page</hi> 38. whilſt he tells them, <hi>That the</hi> French <hi>Churches ſing at the end of the Commandments, theſe four verſes which anſwer to our Lord have mercy upon us and incline, &amp;c.</hi> for this is the very thing that Presbyterians deſire, that theſe words might be uttered at the end of the Commandments, and not at the end of every particular Commandment: <hi>pag.</hi> 45, 46. he takes Mr. <hi>Calvins</hi> pen and drops a very foul blot upon our Church; for the cuſtome of Receiving thrice a year, which is known to be our cuſtome, (for no man is bound to Receive oftner) is by him the called <hi>vitioſus mos, (i. e.)</hi> a vitious cuſtome at leaſt, if not a cuſtome full of vice. But <hi>page</hi> 53. he calls us all, Fools by Craft; for theſe are his words, <hi>That every National Church ought to have <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niformity within it ſelf, hath alwaies been the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:102358:35"/>
judgment of all ſober and wiſe Chriſtians, and is at this day the good example of all the Reformed Churches in the world.</hi> I aſſume, that there ought to be Uniformity in every National Church, hath not alwaies been, nor yet is the Judgment of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> what Concluſion hence ariſes every one ſeeth, but the Concluſion is ſo horrid that I will not form it. My Aſſumption I prove from the Canons of 1640. which are ſo far from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining that there ought to be an Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, that they expreſly allow a Difformity, deſiring in reference to the Rite of doing Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and Obeyſance towards the Eaſt at our coming in, or going out of the Church, that the Rule of Charity preſcribed by the Apoſtle may be obſerved, <hi>(i. e.) That they which uſe this Rite, deſpiſe not them who uſe it not; and that they who uſe it not, condemn not thoſe that uſe it.</hi> And how will the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians rejoyce to read thoſe high commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Churches. 'Tis ſaid <hi>page</hi> 64. <hi>That they are the firſt that Reformed Religion from Popery to True and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtianity:</hi> and <hi>page</hi> 99. 'tis ſaid, <hi>Happy had been all the Christian word, if, as the ſaid Churches were the firſt that Reformed themſelves from Popery, the way of their Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation had been followed by all others who Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed after them.</hi> This his high Opinion he
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:102358:35"/>
confirms by the Teſtimony of Learned <hi>Za<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> and might alſo have confirmed it by the Teſtimony of <hi>Luther.</hi> Well! this being ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed muſt not the Presbyterians carry the day? they think they muſt, and therefore one of them, not many years ſince, Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated <hi>Comenius</hi> into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as making very much for that Plat-form they aimed at. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in the Order of thoſe Churches I find Lay-Presbyters, and which is more, Lay-Presbytreſſes, and Eleemoſynaries anſwering to the Presbyterians Deacons. Officers I know they have called by the name of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtites, which may be rendered Biſhops; but every one of them to ſubmit himſelf to the judgment not only of his Colleagues but alſo of the Conſeniours, and to admit ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, Counſels, and reproof from them, and theſe Conſeniours are together with their Antiſtites to exerciſe Diſcipline upon Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. The Lords day thoſe Churches keep as ſtrictly as the Presbyterians contend to have them kept. Baptiſme they adminiſter without the ſign of the Croſs; with them none are thought to belong to the Paſtoral Cure of Miniſters, but thoſe who do with good will ſubmit themſelves to that Unity and Order; whereas among us every one muſt be a Church Member or elſe go to the Common Goal; and that which anſwers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:102358:36"/>
Confirmation amongſt them is performed only by the Miniſter; and before every Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Maſter of a Family and his Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold come to the Miniſter and are by him examined; ſome few Holy-dayes indeed are kept in theſe Churches, but ſo, that when Divine Service is ended, people go to their work as upon other dayes: There is no order among them to abſtain from the works of their Calling on the Saints day, or to keep the Evening before, Faſt, ſo that theſe Churches are as Presbyterian as Presbyterians themſelves can deſire; what was it then that moved Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> ſo tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendently to extol them? <hi>page</hi> 46. He tells us, That thoſe Churches that firſt Reformed from Popery, receive the Communion kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and it is true, they do ſo; but they did not do ſo from the beginning. In the year 1494. they received the Communion ſtanding, but were forced to leave off that geſture, becauſe their Perſecutors were the more bitter upon that account, and would not this be a goodly Argument think you? the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Church to avoid perſecution receives the Sacrament kneeling, therefore it is conformable with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, that perſecutes all who do not receive the Sacrament kneeling. I but, <hi>when theſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches did joyn with thoſe of</hi> Major Polonia <hi>and</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:102358:36"/>
Lithuania, <hi>it was unanimouſly forbidden to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that bleſsed Sacrament ſitting, becauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other Reaſons, that unmannerly and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reverent geſture was peculiar to thoſe Miſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants the</hi> Arrians <hi>amongſt them, and they made this obſervation, That the cuſtome of ſitting at the Lords Table was firſt brought into ſome of their Churches by thoſe who moſt miſerably falling from their Communion did renounce the Lord who redeemed them, wherefore they intreat and exhort all their Company and Bretheren, that they would change ſitting, into ſtanding or kneeling.</hi> For this Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> refers us to a general Synod celebrated 1583. But every one that looks into the Harmony of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions will ſee that Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> hath not dealt fairly; for firſt, He leaves out a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentheſis of the Synod, in the which it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſaid, <hi>That that geſture of Seſſion with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers is free.</hi> Secondly, Whereas the Synod ſaies that Seſſion was brought in <hi>potiſſimum malo Auſpicio.</hi> This Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> Tranſlates <hi>was firſt brought in.</hi> I grant indeed that in another Synod, to which this Synod doth refer, celebrated 1578. it is expreſly ſaid, That they who fell off to Arrianiſme were the firſt Authors of ſitting in their Churches; but that Synods words Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> does not Tranſlate, and therefore has Tranſlated ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ignorantly or diſhoneſtly. Let it alſo be
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:102358:37"/>
obſerved, that this Synod does pray and beſeech people to leave off ſitting, not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them under the pain of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; yea this Synod by allowing what was done in the former Synod, does determine, <hi>That it is unlawful to ſmite God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men with Eccleſiaſtical Deſcipline becauſe of external Rites.</hi> Let me alſo add, that the Fathers of this Synod were under a miſtake when they ſaid, <hi>That no Church in</hi> Europe <hi>anno</hi> 1583. <hi>did uſe ſitting at the Lords Table,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> is much more miſtaken if he thinks that any <hi>Socinians</hi> firſt brought up the cuſtome of ſitting amongſt us here in <hi>England,</hi> for what if Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> ſaid truly when he confuted the <hi>Socinians, That So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinianiſme had generally ſpread it ſelf into the Nation;</hi> yet ſitting had been uſed before Socinianiſme ſo ſpread it ſelf, I never heard that there was a <hi>Socinian</hi> either in the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, or in the two Houſes untill that one Mr. <hi>Free</hi> got among the Commons, who for his Blaſphemies was caſhiered that Houſe, as I have ſomewhere read.</p>
            <p>Had Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> pleaſed, he might have conſulted a Catechiſme made by <hi>Thomas Beacon</hi> Prebend of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and Printed <hi>cum Privilegio</hi> 1563. in which Catechiſme, the Learned Divine and Godly Confeſſour ſaith; <hi>That if ſitting at the Lords Table,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:102358:37"/>
which was then uſed in certain Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, were recived by publick Authority, and common Conſent, and might be convenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed in our Churches, he could allow that geſture beſt.</hi> And Mr. <hi>Robert Nicholls,</hi> in a Diſcourſe of kneeling in the act of Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, long ſince preſented to Biſhop <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> but not printed till 1660, would have informed him; <hi>That in the beginning of Queen</hi> Elizabeths <hi>Raign, ſtanding was Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained at</hi> Coventry <hi>and</hi> Northampton, <hi>by her Majeſties Commiſſion, and kneeling abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there was another thing perhaps, that might move Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> to be ſo ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlative in the commendation of the <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mian</hi> Churches; namely, a Crotchet got into his head, of calling an Aſſembly of forreign Divines that ſhould all give their ſuffrage for the Diſcipline and Rites of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church: which Crotchet did ſo pleaſe him, that he begins to <hi>call</hi> that Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, <hi>page</hi> 200 and <hi>Comenius,</hi> the only ſurviving Biſhop of the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Churches, he will give the Honour to ſpeak firſt; and accordingly doth bring him in, <hi>pag.</hi> 202, 203, 204, 205. with a long Harangue of words in the commendation of Unity or Order; but is ſo uncivil to the aged Biſhop, as not to allow him liberty to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:102358:38"/>
ſpeak all he had to ſpeak: I muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, out of the Reverence I have for his gray haires, and the reſpect that all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Churches bear to him for his Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Piety, doe him ſo much right, as to let him ſpeak farther about the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies agitated among us: he hath a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raeneſs to the Churches, and by name, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church; in <hi>that page</hi> 146. he tells us what he would have taken from Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy <hi>Secular Dominion, Terrene Riches</hi> or <hi>Wealth,</hi> and <hi>the Pompe of Ceremonies:</hi> and in the next page, brings in the Papiſts laughing and jearing at us for the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies that we retained here in <hi>England,</hi> ſince our Reformation; ſo that I may well conclude, that it had been more for the intereſt of the Church, to have paſſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Churches in ſilence; and it had been well alſo, if the <hi>Conſenſus Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loniae</hi> had never been mentioned; for in that we ſhall find a Synod at <hi>Cracovia, anno</hi> 1573. diſputing <hi>de Choreis,</hi> and when ſome had alledged that there were honeſt as well as diſhoneſt dancings, it was at laſt concluded by the ſuffrage of all, as well Seculars as Clergy, that they were to be condemned according to the Scripture, and to be forbidden unto all that profeſs true Piety. Will it much pleaſe ſome of our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:102358:38"/>
that young Students are by Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> directed to read the Determinations of this Synod, but this is one of the leaſt of the miſchiefs that he doth us; pag. 93. being ſurpriſed with a pang of vain glory, and deſigning to acquaint us with his own Sufferings, he doth not ſtick to deliver that which involves the farre greater part of his preſent Conforming Brethren under the guilt of Rebellion and Schiſme, for theſe are his words, pag. 93. <hi>It is known how great the Perſecution was againſt all Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters who adhered to the King and Church of</hi> England, <hi>during the late troubles, thoſe who were more gently dealt with, were onely plundered, turned out of their Livings, or impriſoned; there were others, whom it was thought fitter to caſt out of the Land, &amp;c.</hi> Out of theſe words, ſuppoſing what is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that they who adhered not to the King and to the Church, are Traytors and Schiſmaticks, thus I argue: All that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hered to King and Church ſuffered, either to Deprivation or Baniſhment, moſt of the preſent Conformiſts, neither ſuffered to Deprivation nor Baniſhment; therefore moſt of the preſent Conformiſts neither adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to King nor Church, and by Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence were Traytors and Schiſmaticks. The <hi>Major</hi> is Mr. <hi>Durells</hi> own; The <hi>Minor</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:102358:39"/>
is known to all the Nation; moſt of the preſent Conformiſts either enjoyed their own Livings during the late troubles, or were put into new Livings. If Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> had enquired of him who Licenſed his Book, he would have told him that he enjoyed a very good Fellowſhip in <hi>All-Souls,</hi> during the late confuſions, but it is uſual with Mr. <hi>Durell,</hi> where he thinks any Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian is within his reach, to lay about him, though he muſt needs ſtrike through the love of moſt of his own Friends. So pag. 44 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> tel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> us, <hi>That thoſe who profeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be Orthodox had either altogether neglected the Sacrament in moſt Pariſhes of theſe three Kingdomes, or elſe had miniſtred it onely to ſome few choice perſons.</hi> Which is to throw dirt into the faces of his Epiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Brethren, for they poſſeſſed moſt of the Pariſhes in this Kingdome to be ſure, and as for the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> there war no neglect of the Sacrament, untill that our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Armies had made it impoſſible for them to exerciſe their Diſcipline. But <hi>Aquilla non capit muſcas,</hi> it is a ſmall thing with Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> thus to ſcratch our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clergy unleſs he alſo wound the whole <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, and that we find him do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; for after he had told us that he would ſet down out of Monſieur <hi>Le Moyne's</hi> Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:102358:39"/>
as much as fitted his purpoſe, he ſets down this, pag. 136. <hi>The Engliſh have a Natural fierceneſs, and withall a natural in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to Superſtition;</hi> Doth this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of our Nation fit Mr. <hi>Durell's</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe? then certainly it is a wicked pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, which cannot be managed but by the cauſleſs aſperſion of a whole Nation: Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Superſtition dwells in the timerous and daſtardly Nature. We, unhappy Mortalls that we be, are naturally fierce, and yet naturally Superſtitious; he that had obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved this concerning us, ſhould have been ſo friendly as to tell us what kind of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition it is, that we are ſo naturally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to, that ſo we might have known how to have watched, and prepared Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes againſt it, if there be any Antidotes ſtrong enough to expell that which is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall. The Author of this Letter whom Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> calls one of the ordinary Preachers to the Reformed Congregation of <hi>Roan,</hi> (which certainly is a Phraſe of diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to <hi>Engliſh</hi> ears) thinkes that upon account of our Natural fierceneſs and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, <hi>We ſtand in need of a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſomewhat Deſpoticall,</hi> that is, of a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by Biſhops; but I would que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry what kind of Biſhops we muſt have: Nature teacheth us to deſire ſome of our
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:102358:40"/>
own Nation, and if they be of our own Nation, are not they Naturally Fierce and Superſtitious too; if they be, what Deſpoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call power ſhall we have to cure them; if they be not, then it ſeems the Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Character expells the Natural Fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Superſtition that dwells in <hi>Engliſh</hi> Natures; but we never yet had any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that a mans being made a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop in <hi>England</hi> did work any cure of his Natural Fierceneſs and Superſtition. Some men have thought that divers after they were advanced to Epiſcopal Dignity grew more fierce and more ſuperſtitious, but this I neither affirm nor deny. In the ſame Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pag. 134. it is ſaid, <hi>That it cannot enter into a Rational Mans Imagination, that a great Kingdome ſhould come by cuſtome to be content to ſee its Biſhops no more, having ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured and reverenced them for the ſpace of one thouſand four hundred years.</hi> This is good news to the Biſhops, and if they can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, they may in <hi>utramque aurem indor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire,</hi> for Epiſcopacy it ſeems as well as Superſtition is grafted into the Natures of the members of this great Kingdome, and they can neither ſuddenly, nor by cuſtome be brought ſo much as to a contentedneſs to want their Hierarchy. The Author of this Epiſtle is famed to be a great Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:102358:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and I doubt not but he is ſo, but me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks he is miſtaken in his Chronology, whileſt he makes this great Kingdome to have reverenced and honoured Biſhops for one thouſand four hundred years. I find not any good evidence that there were any Biſhops among us, till <hi>Auguſtine</hi> the Monk was ſent to us from <hi>Rome,</hi> and it is not one thouſand four hundred years ſince <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> came hither. I ſay there is no good evidence of Biſhops till then, for Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Bede</hi> the onely Author to be regarded concerning matters Eccleſiaſtical, preceding <hi>Auguſtins</hi> miſſion from the Pope, tells us indeed of <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Biſhops, but after he hath ſaid <hi>Epiſcopi</hi> he adds <hi>ſeu Doctores</hi> which renders it very uncertain, what kind of men he means by Biſhops: And Mr. <hi>Petoy</hi> a late Hiſtorian hath adventured to ſay, <hi>That our Church as well as the Scottiſh Church was at firſt planted and Governed without Biſhops, till Biſhops were ſent to us from</hi> Rome. But be this as it will, certain I am, our great Kingdome could not be ſaid to honour and reverence Biſhops, till by the Preaching of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and his Aſſociates, the Nation ceaſed to be Pagan; ſince which time, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops have not alwaies been ſo reverenced and honoured as the Reverend Author of this Epiſtle pretends. Their diſloyalty and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:102358:41"/>
pride rendred them ſo odious in the Reigns of many Kings, that had it been put to the Vote, whether there ſhould have been Biſhops or no Biſhops, it is eaſy enough to ſee how it would have been carried. Nor is it truly ſaid <hi>page</hi> 133. <hi>That we owe our Reformation to the Care and Zeal of our Biſhops, who did ſo wonderfully well repurge the Church of</hi> England <hi>an hundred years ago.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt dawnings of Reformation we owe under God, to <hi>Wickliff,</hi> who was no Biſhop, nor friend to Biſhops; as Biſhops ſignifie men of a ſuperior Order to Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, thoſe who ſealed the Truth with their Bloud, in King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighths dayes, were none of them Biſhops: We can prove from the writings they have left behind them, that they were againſt Biſhops. Seeing this Letter is ſo well penned Mr. <hi>Durells</hi> anger will not wax hot; if I dwell upon it a little longer The Author of it tells us <hi>page</hi> 139 <hi>That he fears not to ſay, if the</hi> French <hi>had kept Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and as many Ceremonies, as would ſerve to fix the attention of the people without Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, they ſhould have ſeen for certain far greater progreſſes of Reformation, and the reſistance of a great many perſons overcome, who are frighttd from their Communion by
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:102358:41"/>
the irregularity of their Government, and the bareneſs of their Service.</hi> I deſign not to put this Reverend Paſtor into any fright becauſe of any thing that he hath ſaid, but really I do not underſtand what he means by [<hi>the Reformed</hi> French <hi>keeping their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi>] for I never heard that they had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Biſhops of their Religion to part with; much leſs do I underſtand upon what he founds his certain aſſeverations that more Papiſts would have come over to them, if they had had Biſhops and more Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. We had before the Wars Biſhops in our Nation, and Ceremonies enough; yet did we not find any great additions made to our Churches by the coming in of Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants. I hope they in <hi>France</hi> can reckon up more Converts from Popery, than we can here in <hi>England,</hi> or elſe Converſions have been but rare. I alſo hope, that ſo many have not apoſtatized among them, as have apoſtatized among us: If they have, <hi>Rome</hi> hath more to boaſt of than I could wiſh. But there is one thing more marvellous than all this; The Author of the Letter thinks, <hi>That if the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Diſſentors have any Charity, they would conſent to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhment of the Epiſcopal Government, though there were ſomething in it they could not approve of: if it were but for the ſake
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:102358:42"/>
of thoſe that follow the Confeſſion of</hi> Aſpurg. For can this learned man think, that Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy, as an Order ſuperiour to Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and as founded upon a Divine Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, would be an Offering well pleaſing to the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Divines? he is not ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with their Writings as that he can ſo think. <hi>If Epiſcopacy upholds the</hi> Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theran <hi>Churches,</hi> as he tells us <hi>page</hi> 138. I am ſure it is not ſuch an Epiſcopacy as we have here in <hi>England;</hi> for ſuch an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy hath no place among them. And oh that it could be ſaid, <hi>That they in</hi> Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke, Norway, Sweden, <hi>and</hi> Germany, <hi>were very quiet under the Epiſcopal Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſeldom ſeen to ſlander and tear one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> We know they have their differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and that none are more moleſted, than the moderate party among them: ſo far was Epiſcopal Government from keeping us quiet in <hi>England,</hi> that the Diviſions and Animoſities did ariſe and grow to a great height among the Biſhops themſelves. Some were told that nothing but their Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks kept them from being Puritans: O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were told, that nothing but their Wives kept them from being Papiſts. Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Parliaments complained to the King of the growth of Arminianiſme, and what did the Church do, to prevent or take away
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:102358:42"/>
the ground and cauſe ſuch Complaints? truly Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> in his Hiſtory of <hi>Laud,</hi> tells us, that there was a Conſultation whether it were meet to bring the thing to a Convocation; but it was concluded, that it was not ſafe ſo to do; becauſe there were too many Members of the Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion inclined to Calviniſme, though there were ſome that were as ſtrangly inclined to Arminianiſme, our Pulpits had not fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ring with Declamations againſt Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagianiſme in ſome places, and againſt Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icall Fatality in others, had not the King by a Proclamation, put ſome ſtop to thoſe Controverſies: ſo that the quietneſs which the Church enjoyed, was rather due to Monarchy than Epiſpacy. Now of late in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeed, <hi>Arnold Polenberg</hi> in his preface to the ſecond Tome of <hi>Epiſcopius</hi> his works, gives us to underſtand, that he deſigned to dedicate that great Folio to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clergy, and particularly to both our Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities; <hi>promiſing himſelf, that almost all the Biſhops of our Churches do defend that Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion concerning Predeſtination, which was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in the Synod of</hi> Dort: Whether he be out in his account, 'tis not for me to enquire, who have work enough to do at home, but it ſeems even in this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans account, all our Biſhops are not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Epiſcopian, and therfore preſerve U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:102358:43"/>
among themſelves, by having their knowledge in thoſe matters unto themſelves. Now if it be found neceſſary to tolerate dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Judgment among the Biſhops themſelves in Doctrines of ſo high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment? it may be worth the Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of thoſe who are in Authority, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they alſo may not be ſuffered to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy Eccleſiaſtical preferment, who differ from their Bretheren only in ſome few points of Diſcipline: I ſay in a few points of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, for as to the eſſentials of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline I am not ſo quick-ſighted, as to find that we diſagree. The things that breed diſcord among us, are ſaid, by thoſe who are the chief cauſes of their impoſition, to be <hi>Adiaphorous, (i. e.)</hi> ſuch things as are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore good becauſe impoſed, rather than im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed becauſe good. On the other hand, thoſe who ſuffer for not yeilding to the Impoſitions, do judge there is ſome evil in the things impoſed, and deſire they may be indulged not to Practiſe them. A Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh man who is not much verſed in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues of Eccleſiaſticall Pollicy, would think no bigger a breach than this, might eaſily be ſtopped up.</p>
            <p>I ſhall diſmiſs this Letter, only adding, That I would not have Mounſieur <hi>Le-Moyn</hi> eſtimated by it, having certain knowledge that he hath both with his tongue and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:102358:43"/>
pen declared, that Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> hath much abuſed him, in leaving out ſundry paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in his Letter wherin he did moderate and regulate the Epiſcopal power, which if they had been inſerted, the Letter would not at all have fitted his deſign.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, it plainly appears, that Mr. <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell</hi> is no obſerver of the Act of Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, for he over and over confeſſeth, that he hath ſuffered thoſe to preach in his Church, who had no Epiſcopal Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is a Crime ſeverely to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by the Act. And I much doubt whether Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> himſelf be qualified to be a Preacher in <hi>England;</hi> for though he make ſhift to tell us, that he was Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by a <hi>Scotch</hi> Biſhop, yet it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable enough, that that Biſhop was Ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Presbyter, by Presbyters; or at leaſt by thoſe, who never had themſelves any Ordination to be Presbyters, but by Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters: and if ſo, there was an error in the firſt Concoction, and we know that is not to be corrected. Our Biſhops lately took care to prevent this ſcruple, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated Mr. <hi>Sharp</hi> firſt Deacon, then Prieſt, then Biſhop, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But we are ſure from Hiſtory, that the firſt Biſhops who came over hither to receive Ordination, were not ſo dealt with: and therefore Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> may do well to conſider upon what ground he
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:102358:44"/>
ſtands, and whether according to the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple now prevailing, he be not ſtill a Laick.</p>
            <p>I have one Catalogue more to give you ſtill, and that will conſiſt of things which Country men call Whiskers; you may if you pleaſe more civilly call them, <hi>Durelliſme,</hi> I ſhall not reckon up all, but yet I muſt be allowed to mention ſome.</p>
            <p>The firſt occurs, <hi>page</hi> 31. <hi>I know none that did ever ſo much as move the queſtion, in what place, and which way the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion Table ought to ſtand, ſo it be ſeated where the people may hear and ſee, except the new</hi> Scotch <hi>and</hi> Engliſh <hi>Presbyterians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A man muſt have a large meaſure of Charity that can think him ignorant, that there were great queſtions moved among our Biſhops themſeves, concerning the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of the Communion Table: and ſome did urge Miniſters to read Service there, though it was demonſtrated that the one halfe of the people could neither ſee nor hear them.</p>
            <p>A ſecond I find <hi>page</hi> 32. <hi>In all Reformed Churches men uſe to enter into the places of Publick Worſhip with their Hats off.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a moſt notorious — nothing being more uſual in ſome Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches than to paſs through and through the places of Worſhip, never ſtirring their Hats: But if he would have the ſaying underſtood of mens putting off their Hats
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:102358:44"/>
when they enter into the place of Publick Worſhip, whilſt the Congregation is Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping, then muſt this ſpeech be placed where it is already placed, among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemans impertinencies.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, page 44. he averrs, <hi>That thoſe who profeſs themſelves to be Orthodox, either altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neglected the Lords Supper for many years in both <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, that of</hi> Oxford <hi>having had no Communion for above</hi> 12 <hi>years; or only admitted ſome few choice perſons to the ſame, refuſing it to all others, though their outward carriage were ſober, honest, and religious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are hundreds of Scholars and Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens know this to be an untruth; no Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian in the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> that had a Paſtoral Charge, or any thing like it, neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to adminiſter the Sacrament for many years, or for any one year; or refuſed any whoſe converſation was ſober, honeſt, and religious. Some of them were blamed for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting ſuch whoſe converſation was not ſo ſober and religious, as all Rules of good Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline do require in Church-members. The phraſe, <hi>That of</hi> Oxford <hi>having had no Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion for above</hi> 12 <hi>years,</hi> perhaps was intended only to bear this ſence, That the Univerſity did not for above 12 years meet together to receive the Sacrament in St. <hi>Maries</hi> before the Terms: If this be any fault, the Presbyterian is not concerned in it. In thoſe 12 years time,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:102358:45"/>
there were but four Vice-Chancellors, all of them right-worthy perſons, but not one of them profeſſing himſelf a Presbyterian. But indeed it may be queſtion'd, whether it was <hi>veri nominis crimen,</hi> not to keep up that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For I wonder who made the Univerſity, as the Univerſity, a Church? or who is the Paſtour of that Church? what Biſhop hath Juriſdiction over it? or who ſhall Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate thoſe Members that come not to the Ordinance? I never heard that ever the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred part of the Univerſity was at that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment when adminiſtred, or that any one man was ever cenſured for being abſent from it: nay I believe the Statute injoyning this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in that Church, will be found a ſpick and ſpan new Statute, coyned on purpoſe to inure the Scholars to Bowing towards the Altar.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, In the ſame page, and the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry next words, we have an Aſſertion as void of all Truth, <hi>viz. That all the Reformed world over, no man that is not a notorious ill Liver is debarred from that Comfort which Chriſt hath left to his Church for the ſick and weak as a Medicine againſt their Diſeaſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had it been ſaid that all the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed World over, no one is to be debarred from the Sacrament by the Rules of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, but a notorious ill Liver, the Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had had ſome modeſty, but what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:102358:45"/>
impudence is it for any man to arrogate ſo much to himſelf as to adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to ſay no man is debarred indeed in all Reformed Churches: others are to be debarred beſides notorious ill Livers, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ignorant and thoſe that have any heretical opinions, which they make known, yea, and all thoſe who cannot ſatisfie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to conform to all the Rites and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies uſed in the Churches, if we may believe Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> himſelf. Yet I trow, there's no neceſſity ſuch ſhould be notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous evil Livers.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Pag. 61. He finds a forehead to leave theſe words on Record, <hi>It is ſaid that the Reformed Churches beyond the Seas take thoſe things in which they differ from the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Church of England, to be ſinful and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they would have her to conform to them.</hi> By whom was this ever ſaid? either in ſo many words, or in any expreſſions tantamount? and how would Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> have this uncouth affirmation to be underſtood? univerſally, or particularly? It ſhould be underſtood univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally, or elſe Mr. <hi>Durell</hi>'s going about to prove the Negative is very needleſs; and if it be ſo underſtood, he might as well have charged us to ſay, that the Reformed Churches count it a ſin in the <hi>Engliſh Church</hi> to uſe her own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Language. The <hi>French</hi> Miniſters preach with their Hats on, did ever Nonconformiſt
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:102358:46"/>
ſay, that they count it ſinful in us to preach with our hats off? or did ever Nonconformiſt go about to bring the <hi>French</hi> mode into his Church?</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Pag. 85. he acquaints us, <hi>That the Reformed Churches beyond the Seas are told, that the Convocations of the Church of</hi> England <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt onely of Archbiſhops and Biſhops, and that the inferiour Clergy are not admitted to ſit and vote in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Till any perſons be produc'd who told the Reformed Churches any ſuch tales, Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> muſt be content to be thought a ſpreader of falſe informations; if he can produce any ſuch, by my conſent let him have the whetſtone and keep it untill he can find Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> telling ſomething that will make him deſerve to have it returned. But he ſhall not need to keep it very long: For</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Pag. 86. he tells us, <hi>That the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in England are to rule by the Conſtitutions and Canons Eccleſiaſtical, and by the Laws of the Land and no otherwiſe; calling alwaies to joyn with them in impoſition of hands, and other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of weighty concernment, ſome of the Prebends of their Cathedralls, or other gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Miniſters of the Dioceſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where was ſhame when this was pen'd? do the Canons require any Biſhop to call any one Miniſter to join with him in impoſition of hands upon a Deacon, or in the Confirmation of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:102358:46"/>
perſons before they are admitted to the Lords Supper? or doth the Biſhop offend againſt any Law or Canon, if he call none of his Miniſters to joyn with him, when a Presbyter is Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated? or is it ſo much as neceſſary, that the Biſhop himſelf ſhould be preſent, when Excommunication is decreed? Is any thing more uſual, then for Lay-Chancellors to decree Excommunication? calling only ſome Miniſter for faſhion ſake to pronounce the ſentence: I would Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> would ſhew us any Reformed Church that hath any ſuch cuſtom; and I wiſh alſo he would tell us, what thoſe Canons and Conſtitutions are, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which our Biſhops are to rule us: For ſome tell us, that they are to proceed not only according to the Canons of 1603. but alſo according to ſundry other Canons that ordinary people know not, nor ever had an opportunity to read of; provided they be not repugnant to the Laws and Statutes of the Nation. Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> 'tis like hath all the 77. Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatine Canons, as alſo the 212 Provincial Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, at his fingers ends; If he can find any Canon among them all, commanding our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops to call in ſome of the Presbyters to joyn with them in impoſition of hands, and all other weighty matters, let him diſcharge it in their faces; yet taking heed left it recoyle, and do himſelf ſome miſchief: For Biſhops do not love to have their power limited, or
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:102358:47"/>
the Canons relating to it expounded, by any but themſelves. I hope no Canons are in force but thoſe of 1603. and by them I am ſure the Biſhop is not required, to call in Presbyters to joyn with him, in every impoſition of hands. In the 31 Canon indeed, <hi>he is appointed to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate Ordinations on the four Sundays after the Ember weeks, and in the Cathedral or Pariſh Church where the Biſhop reſideth, and in the time of Divine Service, in the preſence not only of the Archdeacon, but of the Dean and two Prebenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries at the leaſt; or if they be let or hindred, in the preſence of four Grave perſons, Maſters of Art, and allowed Preachers.</hi> The 35 Canon alſo ſaith, <hi>That the Biſhop ſhall diligently exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine him that is to be admitted to Holy Orders, in the preſence of thoſe that ſhall aſſiſt him at the impoſition of hands; or elſe cauſe the ſaid Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters carefully to examine every ſuch perſon.</hi> All this doth not amount to the calling in of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters to joyn with him in the impoſition of hands. The Book of ordering Prieſts and Deacons, doth indeed require, that the Prieſts that are preſent with the Biſhop, ſhall toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him lay on their hands when a Prieſt is ordained; but how if no Prieſt ſhould lay on his hand, the Ordination is valid however, as is again and again determined by Biſhop <hi>Taylor,</hi> in his Epiſcopacy aſſerted. Yea he ſaith, pag. 197, 198. <hi>That it was declared Hereſie to communicate the power of giving Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:102358:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to Presbyters, either alone or in conjunction with Biſhops.</hi> What he ſaith concerning the Decree of the 4th. Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> pag. 189. I leave to others to examine, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing that I innocently thought, that when our Presbyters laid on hands together with the Biſhop, they as well as he had conferred Orders; Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> in his Hiſtory of Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, pag. 162. hath undeceiv'd me, for theſe are his words: <hi>The conjunction of the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the ſolemnities of this Act, was more for the honour of the Prieſthood, than for the eſſence of the work: Nor did the laying on of the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters hands, conferr upon the party that was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained any power or order, but only teſtified their conſent unto the buſineſs, and approbation of the man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt alſo confeſs that I did not apprehend things aright, in reference to the Biſhop and his Presbyters, untill lately I read in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Biſhop <hi>Taylor,</hi> p. 257, 258. <hi>That to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop is committed the care of the whole Dioceſs He it is who is appointed by peculiar deſignation to feed the flock. The Presbyters are admitted</hi> in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ſollicitudinis, <hi>but ſtill the Juriſdiction of the whole Dioceſs is in the Biſhop, and without the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops admiſſion to a part of it,</hi> per tracit onem ſubditorum, <hi>although the Presbyter by his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation have a capacity of Preaching and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring Sacraments, yet he cannot exerciſe this without deſignation of a particular charge, either
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:102358:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
temporary or fixed,</hi> and p. 262. after he had mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter'd up many Teſtimonies, he tells us, <hi>They ſhew that the Presbyters in their ſeveral charges, whether of temporary miſſion or fixed reſidence, be but Delegates and Vicars of the Biſhop, to aſſiſt the Biſhop in his great charge of the whole Dioceſs,</hi> And p. 282, 283. he hath theſe words. <hi>As I have ſhewn that the Biſhop of every Dſs. did give Laws to his own Church for particulars, ſo it is evident that the Laws of Provinces and of the Catholick Church, were made by Conventions of Biſhops, without the intervening or concurrence of Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters or any elſe, for ſentence and deciſion; The inſtances of theſe are juſt ſo many as there are Councils, and more plainly</hi> 287. <hi>Till the Council of</hi> Baſil, <hi>the Church never admitted Presbyters, as in their own right to voice in Councils and that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil we know ſavor'd too much of the Schiſmatick.</hi> Nay Mr. <hi>Jeans</hi> tells me, <hi>That in the Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which was the last before the late wars, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> Pierce <hi>told the Miniſters of his Dioceſs, that it was an unqueſtionable Priviledge due unto his See, for him to propound unto them the Clerks that they ſhould chooſe, unto which he expected their Conformity,</hi> part. 2. pag. 131. Now if all this ſhould be true, it might be a kind of a Quodlibetical Queſtion, whether in our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations any do ſit and vote beſide the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, for they that ſit not in their own rights, but in the right of others, and as they are De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legates and Subſtitutes, are ſcarce ſaid to ſit:
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:102358:48"/>
And ſo the men whom Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns for falſe accuſations will be found ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to have ſpoken incautelouſly than falſly: As for the other falſe accuſation relating to Archbiſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> that he ſhould make a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy differing from the Liturgies of Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> and K. <hi>James,</hi> and K. <hi>Charles</hi> I. I muſt needs ſay, that is no falſe accuſation. Mounſieur <hi>Chabret</hi> in his Letter recorded, pag. 82. <hi>Doth not ſay that it was reported Archbiſhop</hi> Laud <hi>had compiled a new Liturgy for the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>but onely that a new one was compilled by him: which had occaſioned much clamour, and been the ground of fears and jealouſies.</hi> Now I beſeech Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> to tell me. Did not Arch-biſhop <hi>Laud</hi> compile a Liturgy for the <hi>Scotch</hi> Nation? if he did not, let thoſe who have charged him ſo to do, in allowed writings be confuted; If he did compile that Liturgy, or which is all one, direct thoſe who compiled it; I am ſure it did differ from ours, and occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned much clamour, raiſed many fears and jealouſies, which at laſt ended in a war betwixt the two Nations. Yea, there were ſome few alterations made by the ſaid Archbiſh. or ſome of his Creatures in the Liturgy for our own Church, which were not very well reliſhed by thoſe that never were enemies to the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally eſtabliſhed Government, what thoſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations were may be ſeen in the Dedicatory of Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi>'s <hi>Quench Coal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:102358:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>But I muſt give check to my running pen, and take notice of ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ner failures againſt truth <hi>p.</hi> 8. Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> thus P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſifieth, <hi>Oecolampadius who reformed the City of</hi> Baſil, <hi>is ſtiled Biſhop of that Church upon his Tomb, of which</hi> Bellarmine <hi>himſelf was an eye witnes in his time much againſt his will,</hi> for this we are referred to <hi>Bellar. de notis Eecleſ. l.</hi> 4 <hi>c.</hi> 8. where <hi>Bellarm.</hi> indeed does tell us, <hi>That he was at</hi> Baſil, <hi>and there ſaw the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription on</hi> Oecolampadius <hi>his Tomb, and read it not without laughter.</hi> Now it is hard to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that he ſhould ſee that much againſt his will, the ſight whereof cauſed laughter in him, but the truth is, <hi>Bellar.</hi> laughter was ridiculous, for the words upon the Tomb are not <hi>Primus hujus urbis Epiſcopus,</hi> as <hi>Bellarm.</hi> quotes them, but <hi>Author Evangelicae doctrinae in hac urbe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus: Epiſcopus</hi> indeed he is called, but how? <hi>Hujus Templi verus Epiſcopus,</hi> and if ſuch an <hi>Epiſcopus</hi> will do, Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> any pleaſure, he moſt be a very humourſome man that will envy him ſuch a pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, <hi>Page</hi> 13. He fears not to affirme, <hi>That all underſtanding men among the</hi> French <hi>Churches ſay plainly, that if God Almighty were pleaſed that all</hi> France <hi>ſhould embrace the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion, as</hi> England <hi>hath; the Epiſcopal Government muſt of neceſſity be eſtabliſhed in their Churches.</hi> That all underſtanding men ſhould ſay this and ſay it plainly, is certainly a — all underſtanding men were never heard to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:102358:49"/>
ſpeak about this matter; and ſhould they be called together to ſpeak, they would not utter any ſuch ſpeech as is here fathered on them: it is ſcarce ſence, to ſay if all <hi>France</hi> ſhould em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Reformed Religion as <hi>England</hi> hath; for certainly all <hi>England</hi> hath not embraced the Reformed Religion, the more the pity: and what neceſſity could there be if <hi>France</hi> ſhould generally embrace the Reformed Religion, that Epiſcopal Government ſhould be eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in it? I am not more certain that ever I ſaw the Sun, than I am certain that many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding <hi>Frenchmen</hi> will never be brought to ſay, that Epiſcopal Government muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, <hi>Page</hi> 27. Having told us the <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetick</hi> Confeſſion does vehemently approve of the obſervation of ſome Holy-days, he dreads not to tell us, <hi>That the Miniſters of the Church of</hi> Scotland <hi>ſubſcribed that Confeſſion An.</hi> 1566. <hi>the Miniſters of that Church being then of another Judgment, and of a temper far different from that their Succeſſors have ſhewed of latter years.</hi> Whereas the <hi>Scotch</hi> Miniſters who ſubſcribed the <hi>Helvetick</hi> Confeſſion, ſubſcribed it with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs exception of that part of it which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the obſervation of the Holy-days; and ſo as to that matter plainly ſhewed themſelves to be of the ſame temper and Judgment with their Succeſſors, as plainly appears from the Records of that Church. Let the World judge what credit is to be given to Mr. <hi>Durell</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:102358:50"/>
remote Churches, who relates things ſo contrary to truth about a neigbour Church.</p>
            <p>Eleventhly, <hi>Page</hi> 28. He would perſwade us, <hi>That the Croſses have not been pulled down from the top of Churches, unleſs perhaps in ſom popular Storm;</hi> but we can tell him of Croſſes that have been taken from the top of Churches by the Magiſtrates appointment, and with the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters aprobation, which things are not to be found in a popular Storm.</p>
            <p>Twelfthly, <hi>P.</hi> 29. He bears us in hand, <hi>That the</hi> Bohemians <hi>have ſolemn dedication of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, which Ceremony is to be performed with them by the Biſhop in the ſame manner as with us here in</hi> England. Which words I know not how to reconcile to truth: For what Law is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us enjoyning Churches to be Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a Biſhop; or where may a man find the form and manner of Conſecraring a Church here in <hi>England,</hi> or read the Prayers with the which the Conſecration is to be performed: how ſhall I be able to convince Pariſhoners that they are bound to deſire the Conſecration of their newly built, or newly inlarged Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, or the Biſhop that he is bound to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take this Conſecra.. I though he be not deſired, and muſt the Dioceſan bear the charges of his journey, or have them born by the people, ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry ſuch queſtions as theſe need reſolution, which is a ſign that the Laws and Canons now in force, concern not themſelves at all in this buſineſs of Conſecraition.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:102358:50"/>13thly. <hi>Pag.</hi> 30. Mr. <hi>D.</hi> bears witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Directorians, which is either non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe or a falſity, for theſe are his words; <q>At <hi>Bazil</hi> in the Cathedral Church they have their Fonts of Stone, and uſe them for the baptiſm of Infants as we do here; they have &amp; uſe them alike in the City of <hi>Breme;</hi> and ſo in other places; by which we ſee they are not of the ſame judgment with the Directorians, who find Popery and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition in the very placing of them:</q> If the meaning of theſe words be, that the Directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians find Popery and Superſtition in placing of Fonts as they are placed at <hi>Bazil</hi> and <hi>Breme,</hi> it is a perfect calumny; if the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be that the Directorians find Popery and Superſtition in ſome kind of placing of the Fonts, how can a man thence gather, that they of <hi>Breme</hi> and <hi>Bazil</hi> are not of the ſame judgment with the Directorians: all that the Directory orders is, that Baptiſme be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred in the face of the Congregation, where the people may moſt conveniently ſee and hear, and not in the places where Fonts in the time of Popery were unfitly and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitiouſly placed: Here is no finding of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery and Superſtition in the very placing of Fonts, but onely a prohibiting the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Baptiſme in the places where Fonts in the time of Popery were unfitly and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:102358:51"/>
ſuperſtitiouſly placed; and what, I wonder, could move the Papiſts to place their Fonts where the Congregation could neither hear nor ſee the Miniſter, what I ſay, but meer Superſtition?</p>
            <p n="14">14thly. <hi>Page</hi> 42. He falls again to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſing of Presbyterians, ſaying, <q>That they ought to have as bad an Opinion of the Trine aſperſion of the Croſs in Baptiſme:</q> adding towards the end of that <hi>Page</hi> his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, <q>That if the Trine aſperſion were uſed in our Church, or if ſhe had retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Trine immerſion, as at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of King <hi>Edward</hi> rhe <hi>Sixth</hi>'s Reign, it would be counted a great Superſtition.</q> This is a great ſlander, no Presbyterians that ever I heard of, have any ſuch Principles from which they can charge Superſtition up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Trine immerſion, or upon Trine aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: they ſay, it is the command of God that water ſhould be applied to the Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, had he commanded that this application ſhould be by dipping or ſprinkling once or twice, his command muſt have been obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; ſeeing there is no ſuch Command, they ſay, that Superiours are at liberty to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point which they pleaſe, provided nothing be appointed that is imprudent or uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: and now that we are fallen upon this point, I would gladly know what it is that
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:102358:51"/>
our Church hath appointed; by the Liturgy. I ſee the Miniſter is appointed to dipp the Child in the water, if the Sponſors certifie that the Babe can well endure it; but if they certifie that the Child is weak, it ſhall ſuffice to pour water upon it; ſo that here is no al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of any Rite but Dipping, unleſs there be a Certificate of the Childs weakneſs: But when, I wonder, did any Baptiſt demand ſuch a Certificate? as for the <hi>Quoties</hi> no meaner a man than Biſhop <hi>Mountague</hi> in his Articles of Viſitation poſitively aſſerted, that the Child is thrice to be aſperſed with water on the face: So that the Act of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity notwithſtanding, it ſeems the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the Church were not agreed, and for ought I can obſerve notwithſtanding any Rubrick or Canon now in force, Miniſters are at their Liberty to apply the water once or thrice, though I think Biſhop <hi>Mountague</hi> was much miſtaken, when he ſaid that the Child was thrice to be aſperſed; the Church hath not commanded Trine aſperſion, but there is no <hi>conſtat</hi> that ſhe hath forbidden it. Nor is this the only thing in our Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Baptiſme, about which I am at a loſs. Immerſion I do hugely approve, yea, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee how it can be forborn, unleſs charity or modeſty, on ſomething of that nature do forbid it. But what may be the Reaſon that
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:102358:52"/>
our Church allows not pouring water upon Infants without a Certificate that they are weak; and yet in the form of Baptiſm ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for adult perſons, leaves it wholly at the Miniſters diſcretion, either to dip them into the water, or to pour water upon them. There is another thing in which <hi>aqua mihi haeret.</hi> I am marvellouſly alſo perplext about the Adminiſtrator or Adminiſtratrix of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. In the <hi>Hampton-Court</hi> Conference, K. <hi>James</hi> ſtumbled ſomething at ſome expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in our Liturgy which ſeemed to give Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to women and Maids to Adminiſter Baptiſme in caſe of extreme neceſſity, and he was then anſwer'd by Archbiſhop <hi>Whitgift,</hi> that Baptiſm by Women and Lay-perſons, was not allow'd in the practiſe of the Church, but was enquired of, and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd in the Biſhops Viſitations, and that the words in the Book inferred no ſuch meaning. But Biſhop <hi>Bancroft</hi> declared, that the Church by thoſe words did intend in caſe of neceſſity, a permiſſion of private perſons to Baptize, and that this permiſſion was agreeable to the practiſe of the ancient Churches: Withal opening the abſurdities and impieties of their Opinion who think there is no neceſſity of Baptiſme: I confeſs, I could not but wonder that they who had ſo ſtrongly pleaded for the Liturgy, and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:102358:52"/>
pleas'd themſelves in ſilencing thoſe who could not conform unto it, ſhould be as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary as North and South in expounding a material paſſage of it: But however for the credit of the Ordinance, I rejoyced greatly to find that at the motion of the King, it was ordred that the words, <hi>A Lawful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter,</hi> ſhould be put into the Rubrick, for by this means I thought us ſufficiently ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt any female Baptizers. But he who doth not love to conceal any thing Dr. <hi>P. H.</hi> in his neceſſary Introduction to the Hiſtory of Biſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> pag. 27. hath quite took away the cauſe of my rejoycing; for he ſaith, <q>The alteration was greater in ſound than ſenſe, it being the Opinion of many great Clerks, that any man in caſes of extreme neceſſity, who can pronounce the words of Baptiſm, may paſs in the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of &amp; account of a lawful Miniſter.</q> By any man, I ſuppoſe, he means any one that is <hi>de humano genere,</hi> and by conſequence either a Child or a Natural; but I hope ſome one will give check to this extravagant Notion, that ſo a ſtop may be put to the Licentiouſneſs of thoſe, unto whom God hath no more given a power to Baptize, than to Ordain Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. And therefore I wiſh that to ſtop this gap, inſtead of the Miniſter of the Pariſh, or any other lawful Miniſter, it had been ſaid,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:102358:53"/>
the lawful Miniſter of any other Pariſh; and then I ſhould have thought it impoſſible for any man to be ſo impudent as to opine that our Church had not reſtrained Baptiſme to the Clergy. But they who made our new Liturgy were wiſer then I; and ſome that have ſubſcrib'd it, it ſeems had got ſome ſuch way of Interpretation as no Logick ever led me into.</p>
            <p n="15">15thly. <hi>Pag.</hi> 103. He makes bold with the whole Church of <hi>England:</hi> For of her, theſe are his words: <q>She holdeth ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of Miniſters in the Chriſtian Church to be of Apoſtolical, nay, of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitution, having as ſhe conceiveth for Grounds of this her Judgment beſides Scripture, the Practiſe of the Holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in their time, of the Univerſal Church ever ſince, until this later Age; and which is more, of Chriſt himſelf, who ordained the Apoſtles, and the Seventy Diſciples in an imparity as two diſtinct Orders of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in his Church.</q> I ſuppoſe this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Praedicant doth not pretend to any faculty of diſcerning the ſecret thoughts and inward conceptions of our Churches heart, farther then when ſhe diſcov'rs them by ſome words or other ſignification; let him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tell us where the Church hath declared her ſelf thus to hold, thus to conceive as in
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:102358:53"/>
the fore-quoted words is repreſented, That the Church holds ſubordination of Miniſters to be an Apoſtolical Inſtitution is plain e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; and therefore Mr. <hi>D.</hi> beats the Air as oft as he brings any Teſtimonies for Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacie, which do not place it among Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Inſtitutions: but I cannot finde that the Church any where diſtinguiſheth Apoſtolical and Divine; much leſs doth ſhe ſay, that ſhe hath beſides Scripture the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Apoſtles, and of Chriſt himſelf. The Practice of the Apoſtles and Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf are recorded in Scripture, and be a part of Scripture, and therefore it is not ſenſe to ſay that ſhe hath theſe Arguments beſides Scripture, unleſs ſhe thinks that theſe are not Scriptural Arguments: Beſides, where doth our Church ſay, <hi>Chriſt ordained the Apoſtles and Seventy Diſciples in an imparity, as two diſtinct Orders of Miniſters in his Church;</hi> poſſibly ſome Writers of our Church may ſo ſay, our Church, I believe will never be found to have ſaid any ſuch thing: if ſhe have, the Speech hath given her Adverſaries too much advantage, for they will ask in what order Chriſt placed the Seventy? If in the Order of Presbyters how came ſome of them afterwards to be made Deacons as it is generally held that ſome of them were in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p n="16">
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:102358:54"/>16thly. <hi>Pag.</hi> 144. He leaves upon record 4 great Untruths, and yet makes them or 3 of them to be Truths known to all the three Kingdoms: they all relate to the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, the firſt is, <q>That they had no ſet Forms, nor indeed would admit of any whether for Common-Prayer, or Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Sacraments, Matrimony, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> How doth he know they had no ſet Forms for theſe, or ſome of theſe? I believe ſundry of them had Forms, or <hi>quaſi</hi>-forms for all theſe, and I am confident the Major part of them would, if need required, ſwear that they never declared that they would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any ſet Forms for theſe. But Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he ſaith, <q>That for a long time many of them had left off uſing that very Form our Lord hath taught us:</q> 
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 37. he had ſaid, <hi>That moſt if not all the Directorians had for a long time here in</hi> England <hi>left it out of their Service:</hi> But wiſely then adds, <hi>It will be hard to make Tranſmarine Brethren be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that there were any ſuch men among us.</hi> And certainly it will be impoſſible to make our own Nation believe that this had any truth in it; for it is known all the Nation over, that thoſe whom he muſt mean by the Presbyterians, did many, if not moſt of them, and that very often, uſe the Lords Prayer, though they did not think it their
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:102358:54"/>
Duty to uſe it every time they officiated in publick. I my ſelf for ſome years attended upon a Lecture in this Nation, carried on by thirteen perſons, as<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of them uſed the Lords Prayer, and uſually concluded their Prayers with it. I ſhould wrong the Engliſh Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Nonconformiſts ſhould I not here acknowledg that they have very wel deſerv'd of the Church of Chriſt by their Pious and Learned Diſcourſes and Sermons upon the Lords Prayer: I believe no Church can ſhew a more full and profitable Treatiſe of it than that compoſed by Mr. <hi>John Ball,</hi> and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by his loving Friend Mr. <hi>Simeon Aſh,</hi> towards the end of a Book, Entituled, <hi>The Powwer of Godlineſs;</hi> nor do I know that ever the uſe of the Lords Prayer was more fully Apologiz'd for, againſt the Exceptions of the Browniſts and others, than by Mr. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Thom. Hodges,</hi> the one ſundry years ſince dead in the Lord, the other ſtill in the Land of the Living. Oh that I had ſo much reaſon to commend the Zeal of all the Epiſcopal Miniſters of my Acquaintance! But indeed I have not; Sundry of them whoſe parts I greatly eſteemed I have known to conclude their Prayers before Sermon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any uſe of the Lords Prayer, as oft as they could conceive that there was any Great Perſon in the Congregation, who
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:102358:55"/>
would think the worſe of them for uſing it.</p>
            <p>To conclude this buſineſs, I Queſtion not but it is both lawful and expedient to uſe the Lords Prayer, as a Prayer as well as a pattern; but let not Mr. <hi>D.</hi> too ſeverely cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure thoſe who cannot as yet obtain leave of themſelves to uſe it as a Prayer, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at ſuch times when they have before prayed largely both for themſelves and others; for where can he find a Law ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it our duty to uſe thoſe words com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the Lords Prayer, any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than as a pattern and example of our Prayers. I know he ſomewhere produceth the words of St. <hi>Luke, When ye pray, ſay, &amp;c.</hi> But were thoſe words brought into the form of a Syllogiſm, it would not to the Browniſts themſelves appear very formidable; for they will ask what the words be that Chriſt there commands to uſe: if it ſhould be anſwered them, the words that follow in St. <hi>Lukes</hi> Goſpel, then would they reply, that all who tye themſelves to the uſe of our Engliſh Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy would be tranſgreſſours of this Law; for no where in all the Liturgy does the Lords Prayer occur as it is recorded in St. <hi>Lukes</hi> Goſpel. Indeed the Compilers of our Liturgy do neither follow St. <hi>Matthew</hi> nor St <hi>Luke,</hi> but vary from them both, as
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:102358:55"/>
will appear to any that ſhall compare the Lords Prayer in the Liturgy, with the Lords Prayer in the New Teſtament, whether of the laſt or former Tranſlation. But if it ſhould be ſaid to them that the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment requires only that words be uſed to the ſame ſenſe and purpoſe with thoſe in St. <hi>Luke;</hi> then is the Browniſt at as great Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty as he could wiſh; They who lay it as a burden upon our Conſciences to uſe the ſame words in Engliſh that the Evangeliſts uſed in Greek, ſhould do well clearly to ſatisfie us, what words were uſed by the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, for in no other matter do the Copies more vary. I have enough to ſatisfie my ſelf, that the Doxology in <hi>Matthew</hi> was not added in later times, as ſome think; but if any one ſhould differ from me in this Opinion, I ſhould be loath to tye my ſelf neither to eat nor drink, till I had convinced him. <hi>Grotius</hi> tells me that it is in the Syriack and Arabick Tranſlations, yea, and in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine too; but I am ſure it is not in that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabick Tranſlation exhibited to us in our late <hi>Polyglotts,</hi> and it is in very few Latine Tranſlations, if any that are conſiderable. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> is wanting in the very Syriack Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which all Scholars acknowledge to be ancient; but how ſhall I be able to perſwade a diſſenter, that this Syriack Tranſlation,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:102358:56"/>
which we follow, is the Ancienteſt in that kind; If it be the Ancienteſt, then muſt I needs acknowledge that from thence may be fetched a very good Argument for the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity of Holy-dayes: But perhaps it is not the Ancienteſt: that which <hi>Immanuel Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melius</hi> followed, having no ſuch Inſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and various Titles; by which is ſignified that theſe and the other things were done certain dayes in the Year; How ſhould I convince him that would ſay, <hi>Our Father</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not, <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven,</hi> or him that would uſe fewer Petitions by two, then we commonly uſe, or him that would not ſay, <hi>Amen,</hi> at the end of the Prayer. Above all things this makes me that I dare not too confidently aſſert that our Lord Jeſus intended to make it the Duty of his Diſciples after his departure to uſe thoſe very words which he delivered to them, becauſe I do not find in thoſe words any mention of his own moſt ſweet &amp; preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Name: whereas when he comes to give them a ſtanding Directory for Prayer, he enjoyns them, <hi>John</hi> 16. to ask in his Name, aſſuring them that Prayers made in his Name ſhould be anſwered, but letting them know withal, that at that time they had never as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked any thing in his Name, what ſhall we ſay to this? If we ſhould ſay, that the Apoſtles,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:102358:56"/>
Chriſts Directions notwithſtanding, had never uſed his Prayer, the Browniſts will make an advantage of ſuch a Confeſſion; if we ſhould ſay, that though they uſed the Lords Prayer, yet by uſing of it they had not prayed in the Name of Chriſt, <hi>i. e.</hi> explicite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſo as they were to do, after they had a more explicite knowledge of the Nature and Offices of Chriſt; then though this prayer will ſtill contain all needful matter to be prayed for, yet it will admit of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, whether our prayers are not to be ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered unto God in ſuch phraſes and forms as do more diſtinctly mention the Death, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and Interceſſion of our Bleſſed Mediator. Granting the Doxology to be a part of the Lords Prayer, as I am of a ſtrong Opinion it is, it is plain that is is not ſo diſtinct and particular as ſome others in the Epiſtles and Revelations be, which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer and aſcribe praiſe and Glory unto God by Chriſt, as <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.21. or unto Chriſt, as 1 <hi>Timothy</hi> 6.16. or to God and the Lamb Chriſt Jeſus, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.13. Later Doxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies do make an acknowledgment of the Bleſſed Trinity as to every Perſon. <hi>Glory be to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Ghoſt:</hi> and it ſeems but meet that the Doxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies of Chriſtians (properly ſo called) ſhould have ſomething in them, to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:102358:57"/>
them from the Doxologies and Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations not only of Heathens, but alſo of Jews. There be ſome that ſay our Lord took this form of prayer out of the Jewiſh Liturgies, and one undertakes to give us an account from the Jewiſh Liturgies, of that variety and difference that is to be found in the recital of it in <hi>Mathew</hi> and <hi>Luke, viz.</hi> he would have us think that the prayer, as in <hi>Mathew</hi> was intended for the Diſciples more publick uſe, as in <hi>Luke</hi> for their more private uſe: But in all this that Learned Man does need a credulous Reader, who will not too ſtrictly enquire into the grounds of his aſſeveration; Moſt plain it is, that our Savior made this Prayer for his Diſciples, whileſt they were Members of the Jewiſh Church, and before he had blotted out the Hand-wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Ordinances, or had ſent the Spirit to lead them into all Truth: let it therefore be conſidered, whether we are not rather ordinarily to expreſs our ſelves in a Dialect more ſutable to the New Teſtament Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, than is uſed in the Lords Prayer, yet uſing that prayer alſo, as a prayer, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it the patern and example, as to the things to be prayed for, in all the prayers that we make; and let men have a care how they adventure to conclude their own pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers:] thus we further pray unto thee in that
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:102358:57"/>
very form of words which Chriſt himſelf hath taught us,] till they have made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves certain what form of words Chriſt did uſe when he directed his Diſciples. 3dly. he ſaith, <q>Moſt of them had likewiſe whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neglected the uſe of the Lords Supper for many years.</q> He might with as much truth have ſaid, that moſt of them for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years had lived without eating and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; The moſt of them miniſtred the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments frequently, and I know where they have been blamed for adminiſtring it too frequently; if this Characterizer ſay this is not a truth, he may chance in a ſhort time by printed Teſtimonials to ſee himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed: But he hath not done, but for a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion tells us, <q>There was a great irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence at Prayer in their Congregations, very few kneeling, many not ſo much as putting off their Hats, and of this, he ſaith, he was an Eye-witneſs.</q> I demand only whether he think it be irreverence for a man not to kneel in the publick Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in time of Prayer? Whether ſtanding be not a poſture of Reverence? Whether in the <hi>London</hi> Churches it be not morally im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for the one half of the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to kneel in time of Prayer? Into how many Congregations he went where many did not ſo much as put off their Hats in the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:102358:58"/>
time of Prayer? And whether he either ſaw or heard that the Miniſters of thoſe Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es did any way countenance that irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence? If he cannot anſwer theſe Queſtions roundly and readily, oh, what work hath he made for an accuſing Conſcience! For ought I know thoſe in whom he obſerved this irreverence, might be Sectaries, who did more bitterly inveigh againſt Presbyterians than againſt any other men whatever; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps alſo they might be Epiſcopal-men, who deſigned to put an affront upon the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians Prayers: juſt as now ſome are obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to ſit upon their Breech all the time of Pulpit-prayer, unleſs when juſt the Lords Prayer is repeating, becauſe forſooth Pulpit-prayer is not allowed by the Church, but onely bidding of Prayer. I write it with grief, but I muſt write it, I never in any Congregations where I have been, obſerved ſo much irreverence as I have obſerved in thoſe in which there is the greateſt abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of ſuch as alwayes pretended a love to the Engliſh Liturgy; particular Stories I might relate, and would relate did I not fear to ſet deluded people at a greater diſtance from our Aſſemblies; but if Mr. <hi>D.</hi> will call for them, he ſhal have them by the peck &amp; by the buſhel; I need not ſtay about theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars: the World I truſt will not long want
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:102358:58"/>
ſufficient information how much the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians have been abus'd by Mercenary Pens.</p>
            <p>I have only two Animadverſions on this Authors Sermon, and then your trouble will not be much longer continued. <hi>Pag.</hi> 20. He tells us, <hi>That thoſe who have Devotion and leiſure enough to come to Church, and be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at Divine Service may hear the whole Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble read every year, the Old Teſtament once, and the new no leſs than thrice.</hi> A man ſcarce knows where to be preſent at Divine Service every day morning &amp; evening, unleſs at ſome Cathedral or Collegiate Church; for though all Prieſts and Deacons are appointed to ſay daily the Morning and Evening Prayer, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther privately, or openly, not being let by Sickneſs, or ſome other urgent cauſe, and though Curats be appointed being at home, and not otherwiſe reaſonably hindred, to ſay the Prayers in the Pariſh Church, or Chappel, and to toll the Bell that the people may come and hear the word and pray with them, yet the Aſſenters, and Conſenters that do this, are as rare as black Swans, and if a man had health and Devotion ſo much as to inable him to attend upon the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dral Service Morning and Evening from the firſt of <hi>January</hi> to the laſt of <hi>December,</hi> yet ſhould he not by that means hear the whole
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:102358:59"/>
Bible read, either the Old Teſtament once, or the New Teſtament thrice, there being ſeveral Chapters ia both, that are never ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be read.</p>
            <p>Whether the Church do well to appoint above an hundred of Apocryphal Chapters to be read, and about an hundred eighty eight Canonical Chapters, never to be read, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, certainly he that would adventure, in a Sermon to ſay, <hi>de facto, That the Church had appointed the whole Bible to be read over once a year, had taught his tongue not much to regard Truth:</hi> So had he alſo who adventured to ſay, <hi>pag.</hi> 23. <hi>That it is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the people that they repeat aloud the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of ſins;</hi> No ſuch thing is required of the people, rather it is required that they ſhould repeat the Confeſſion of ſins with a lowly and ſubmiſs voice; Should all lift up their voyces aloud, there might be more confuſion then Mr. <hi>D.</hi> is aware of.</p>
            <p>But though I am confident Mr. <hi>D.</hi> is mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken about the two laſt mentioned particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, yet I muſt profeſs I am not clear about the Churches meaning in either of them: Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter order taken for the reading of the Pſalms, we are thus directed, <q>Then ſhall be read diſtinctly with an audible voice the firſt Leſſon taken out of the Old Teſtament, as is appointed in the Kalendar <hi>(except, &amp;c.)</hi>
               </q>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:102358:59"/>
Any man by this would think that the firſt Leſſon were alway by the Kalendar appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be taken out of the Canonical Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the Old Teſtament; yet the Kalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar appoints many Apocryphal Chapters to be read for the firſt Leſſon: Is Apocrypha become a part of the Old Teſtament? I know our Church had no intention to make it ſo, yet the Phraſe uſed by her in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex Notion, ſounds as if ſhe did; I ſuppoſe therefore ſhe calls all Books preceding the New Teſtament, whether Canonical or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocryphal by the name of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; If this ſuppoſition hold, than the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition to all Miniſters Eccleſiaſtical pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed to the Second Book of Homilies will warrant them to change all the Chapters A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocryphal that ſhall fall in courſe to be read on every Sunday or Holiday into a Chapter of the New Teſtament; for in that Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition ſuch Liberty is granted, or rather ſuch courſe is preſcribed in reference to the leſs edifying Chapters of the Old Teſtament. But perhaps by aſſenting and conſenting to all and any thing, Miniſters have given a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their liberty to make any ſuch exchange. Let thoſe whom it concerns conſider. Where I live I have little opportunity to hear Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crypha read publickly, and if in my Family I make choice of Divinely inſpired Writings
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:102358:60"/>
to read, I hope I am no tranſgreſſour of the Law.</p>
            <p>Nor really do I know what is meant in our Liturgy by a loud voice; In the old Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer Book after the abſolution the Miniſter was appointed to begin the Lords Prayer with a loud voice, In the new, <hi>loud</hi> is changed into <hi>audible,</hi> and we are alſo requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at that time to repeat it after the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, which was not required in the old. But now coming to look upon our directions for the rehearſing of the Lords Prayer, after the repeating of the Creed, I find that not only the Miniſter, but Clerks and people are appointed to ſay it with a loud voice. I cannot think the phraſe is meerly varied by Chance, nor yet do I ſee the Reaſon of the variation, nor do I obſerve any, either Prieſts or people, thus to vary by ſtraining their voice higher at one time than another. Perhaps our laſt Amenders of the Liturgy did put audible, inſtead of loud, in ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; that we might know that voice was loud enough on the Miniſters part which the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple could hear; but what ſhall be called ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an audible or loud voice on the peoples part? Are thoſe people that kneel at one end of the Church to ſpeak ſo loud as they may be heard of thoſe who kneel at the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end, or loud enough to be heard of the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:102358:60"/>
Miniſter, or only loud enough to be heard of thoſe who are next to them. Mr. <hi>D.</hi> hath had many occaſions and opportunities to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and conſent to all and every thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and preſcribed, and therefore is ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of none of theſe things; Let him be him be intreated to help us poor Ingrams; for our Countrey Prieſts are as unable to untie theſe knots as our ſelves.</p>
            <p>All this I have written, not out of any diſlike to thoſe who put out their Books in the defence of the Engliſh Liturgy, for I ſhould be right glad of the pains of any who would juſtifie it againſt all the Objections with which it is preſſed; provided he would do it like a Scholar and like a Chriſtian, grounding whatever he writes upon ſuch Reaſons as are apt to move thoſe who have Conſciences, and do remember that God will bring them to a ſtrict account for all that they do in his Worſhip; but Mr. <hi>D.</hi> evidently is no meet perſon to make our Churches defence; for he has been ſo highly rewarded, is ſo overwhelmed with Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Preferments, and Dignities, that the World will hardly think any thing put him upon writing beſides filthy lucre. If he would have done our Church ſervice, be ſhould have contented himſelf with ſome one Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Preferment, ſpending himſelf in that,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:102358:61"/>
going to his people, from houſe to houſe, perſwading them to credit the Liturgy, by excelling all thoſe in Virtue that uſed no Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy; he ſhould have conjur'd them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny all ungodlineſs, and worldly luſts, and to uſe their beſt wiſdom ſo to order their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, as that they might have leiſure to come Morning and Evening every day, and receive the benefit of their Churches Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy: but as the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>That they who themſelves were circumciſed kept not the Law:</hi> ſo we ſay, that they who have aſſented and conſented, do not obſerve the Orders and Rules to which they have given aſſent and conſent, nor yield that Obedience which they have ſworn to yield: How few be they that Catechiſe half an hour every Sunday and Holiday? How few be they that have called and advertiſed notorious evil-livers not to approach the Lords Table, until they have truly repented and amended their naughty lives? How many have ſubſcribed the Articles who never ſo much as read the Homilies that by the Articles they are to approve? I once happened into the Company of the Rectour of a Pariſh, who ſignifying to me that he had lately been with the Biſhop to receive Orders from him, I asked what things were required of him in order to Ordination? He told me among other things, he had ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:102358:61"/>
the three Articles in the 36 Canon: but when I demanded of him what thoſe Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles were, he confeſſed he knew not what they were, nor had he ever ſeen them, but followed his Leader: and not long ſince, one had confidence enough to come to a Reverend Miniſter of my acquaintance with a purpoſe to perſwade him to Conformity; but my Friend arguing for his Non-conformity from a very plain paſſage in the Liturgy, he denied that there was any ſuch paſſage to be found; and had not this man then well read and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died the Book, to which he ſo ſolemnly gave aſſent and conſent. I profeſs where-ever I come, I make it my buſineſs to reconcile people to the publick Aſſemblies, my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience would fly in my face if I ſhould do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe; but I find my ſelf unable to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with them through the prejudice they have taken up againſt the Liturgy, and their prejudices are grounded for the moſt part upon the wicked lives of thoſe that are the moſt conſtant Readers and frequenters of it. I ſhall never upon this account ceaſe to joyn in prayers and to hear Sermons; but yet I rejoyce that a great Prelate lately in his Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation openly declared in his Speech, his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to proceed, and deal more ſeverely againſt thoſe who ſhould be found looſe and profane, than againſt thoſe that differed from
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:102358:62"/>
him only in Ceremonies, The Lord give hearts to thoſe whom it concerns, to think immorality worthy of preſentment, and to ſet a mark upon all whoſe feet run into all exceſs of Riot, and whoſe Tongues are ſet on fire from Hell, that ſo we may have where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to ſtop the mouths of thoſe who are bent upon Separation, and employ their Rhetorick in nothing more, than in perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the people that God is departed from us: It would be a ſmall trouble to me to find the Non-conformiſts diſarmed, did I find the Weapons of their Warfare put into the hands of thoſe, who would uſe them more, to the diſadvantage of the World, Fleſh, and Devil.</p>
            <p>I have mentioned one thing that makes Mr. <hi>D.</hi> not the fitteſt perſon in the World to manage this Controverſie, that is, his not being free from, at leaſt the ſuſpicion, of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs. I will ſuggeſt one or two more: He ſeems to be very injudicious, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore puts into his Book ſuch cold Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of Church and Liturgy, as do only not diſpraiſe it. I inſtance only in Monſieur <hi>Vauqueline,</hi> whom he brings in <hi>Pag.</hi> 189. thus extolling our Liturgy, <hi>The Book of Common Prayer is very far from any Idolatry, and there is not in it any formal Superſtition.</hi> Is not this a rare Elogium? But above all he diſparages
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:102358:62"/>
himſelf by giving flattering Titles unto men, <hi>Pag.</hi> 87. he tells us that Monſieur <hi>Goyen is as verſed in Antiquity as poſſible;</hi> a Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion too high to be given to any man, and ſuch as that Reverend perſons worth will never ſuffer him to accept of, or ſo much as to commend the love of him who gave it; let any one read the Epiſtle Dedicatory to his Book, he will find the Lord Chancellour ſo highly commended, that any one may ſee the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations were rather given to his Place, than to his Virtues; all the Authority of the Nation hath lately ſentenced him to Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and yet Mr. <hi>D.</hi> could not find ſo much humility, as either to bewail his fault, or his unhappineſs, who had beſtowed ſuch praiſes, in a printed letter upon him, whom the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom has declared to have deſerved ill of it, and of the Church too.</p>
            <p>I may well think you will begin to ſay what is all this to the Latine Book that I ſent you? Or how can I by all you have hitherto writ, perceive your Judgment about it? Surely, Sir, the things I have noted out of the Engliſh Book, are ſufficient to let you ſee, that his 2d. Book is not worth your reading; Scarcely can you find more words put together to leſs purpoſe. The very Title-Page ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently expoſes him either to the ſcorn, or pity of thoſe whom he choſe for his Adverſaries.
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:102358:63"/>
               <hi>Vindiciae Sacrae Eccleſiae Anglicanae:</hi> What is this <hi>Holy Engliſh Church?</hi> Does he mean that Company of men and women in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> who exerciſe themſelves therein, that they may be holy as God is holy: <hi>Quis La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedaemoniorum vituperat?</hi> Why is this Church vindicated that no ſober man ever went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to accuſe? If by the Holy Church of <hi>England</hi> he mean the late Convocation, then he hath written as our Epiſcopal men are wont to write; and by the Canons of 1603. it is made a very dangerous point, to deny <hi>that a Convocation is the Church of England by Repraeſentation;</hi> and I have no mind to try how near I can come to that danger without incurring it; Seeing Mr. <hi>D.</hi> has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed with thankfulneſs, that he learned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity under <hi>Amyraldus;</hi> he may do well to try whether he can confute his Maſter in his <hi>Theſes de Eccleſia nomine, ac definitione,</hi> and, <hi>de ratione convocandorum Conciliorum;</hi> which do not look very ſmilingly upon that form of Speech which we uſe in <hi>England,</hi> or upon the way of conſtituting our Convocations. Mr. <hi>Jeanes</hi> a man of a very Scholaſtical Head, had called the Convocation, <hi>The Church of England:</hi> but in the Second part of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, he wonders upon what account he or any one elſe could think it to be the Church of <hi>England;</hi> he inſtances in his own Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:102358:63"/>
in which there was one Dean, one Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bend, three Arch-Deacons; whereas the whole Clergy of the Dioceſs choſe but two; ſo that he thinks our Convocations may be rather called Repraeſentatives of the Biſhops and Cathedrals, than of the Church of <hi>En-England:</hi> And he asks whether if the King ſhould chuſe two hundred into the Houſe of Commons, and the people one, that Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing could be called the Repreſentative of the People of <hi>England?</hi> Mr. <hi>D.</hi> who has uſed this Title ſhould have done well to give ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to ſuch kind of Queſtions is theſe, and to have ſhewed us Synods in other Churches, the Major part of the Members whereof, are neither choſen by the people, nor by the Clergy; inſtead of doing ſo, he hath left it doubtful, what he means by the Church: And it is much more doubtful to me whom he means by his Schiſmaticks: againſt whoſe vociferations he pretends to defend his Church: When you have called a man Schiſmatick, you have call'd him every thing: but I believe no man in the world thinks that all thoſe againſt whom he vents his ſpleen in this Book, deſerve to be called Schiſmaticks. I am ſure according to the definition of Schiſme, that is given by Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> they are not Schiſmaticks: Mr. <hi>D.</hi> ſeems to thruſt out his ſharpeſt ſting againſt Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:102358:64"/>
Now it is notoriouſly known that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly went to the publick Congregation: its known alſo that he has in the publick Congregation received the Sacrament of the Lords Supper according to the form that is by Law eſtabliſhed: he has Communion with the Church of <hi>England</hi> in all Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, takes a great deal of pains to reſolve the doubts of thoſe who ſcruple Communion with her, and yet is in Mr. <hi>D</hi>'s account one of the Heads of the Schiſmaticks; Let him take heed that he do not throw this dirt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch mens faces, if he do, it will fly back into his own. The Caſe of hundreds of Non-conformiſts ſtands thus: When they were School-boyes, or Under-graduates in the Univerſity, the King called the ſo much talked of Long-Parliament; in which both the <hi>High-Commiſſion Court,</hi> and <hi>Star-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> were taken downa; nd the High-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion Court was taken down in words ſo general, as were interpreted to reach all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Eccleſiaſtical Jurisdiction and coercive power of Church Conſiſtories: by theſe two Statutes Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> ſayes. That the <hi>two great Bulwarks of the Church were beaten down;</hi> In the ſame Parliament alſo paſſed an Act diſabling the Biſhops to ſit as Members in the Houſe of Peers; in this condition ſtood things until an unhappy War was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:102358:64"/>
betwixt the King and the two Houſes, during the beat of which War, the two Houſes Voted away the Epiſcopal Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment eſtabliſhed in the Nation; and Biſhops, in the places where their Forces prevailed, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were not at all, or ſhewed not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; Divine Providence ſo ord'red it, that the Kings Forces were at laſt quite overcome, and with them Biſhops alſo were overcome; ſo as they no where publickly and ſolemnly own'd either their Power of order, or Jurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: ſo ſtood affairs until that his Majeſty was reſtored; but in the mean time young men that had applied themſelves to the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Divinity, were under neceſſity either by the Statutes of Colledges, or by accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Livings, to enter into Holy Orders, and to receive thoſe Holy Orders from meer Presbyters; by which Orders they acted for many Years, the Lord accompanying their Miniſtry with great ſucceſs, the people every where receiving the Euchariſt at their hands, and bringing their Children alſo to be baptized by them; the Parliament which had the happineſs to bring in the King, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming them in their Livings; but the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament hath thought meet to en-act that all ſhould be uncapable of Cure of Souls that had not Epiſcopal Ordination; ſo as they finding themſelves under this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemma,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:102358:65"/>
that either they muſt nullifie their former Orders by Re-ordination, or elſe quit their Livings, choſe to relinquiſh their Benefices, &amp; ſo made way to the preferment of many every way of Mr. <hi>D</hi>s own mind; He himſelf perhaps he had not had ſo many Eccleſiaſtical Benefices, and Dignities, could they have ſatisfied themſelves to keep their ſtations; this is the Schiſme of a great ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe with whom he is ſo angry: And can be not forgive them ſuch a Schiſm which proved ſo beneficial to himſelf and others? It will be more difficult to forgive Mr. <hi>D.</hi> the Schiſme that he himſelf endeavours to make contrary to the <hi>Intent of the Act of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity,</hi> and <hi>Oblivion,</hi> by which we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to bury the Actings of thoſe that were indemnified in the Grave, ſo as not to mention them to the diſparagement of any, but leave them wholly to the Judgment of the Great day; but this bitter man, as if he envied Church, and State, the Peace, and Quietneſs they both enjoy, will needs open the Grave of Oblivion, rake into the duſt, and bring all old Stories and Tranſactions upon the Stage again. Would any man be like minded; how eaſie were it to recri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate; Who knows not that a <hi>Primate of England, and Metropolitan</hi> took up Arms in the Cauſe of the two Houſes, and had Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:102358:65"/>
Voted him for his good Service? Was not the Author of <hi>Politica Sacra &amp; Civilia,</hi> an Epiſcopal Divine? Doth he not at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Conform? Is he out of his Living, who writ the <hi>Jus Divinum Regiminis Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtici?</hi> If we ſhould make ſearch into our <hi>Biſhops, Deans, Prebends, Prieſts,</hi> might we not finde ſuch as took the Covenant them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and perſwaded others to take it? Nay, might we not among them, even among them, find thoſe that took the Engagement, and came into the Livings of thoſe that were outed for not taking the Engagement? Nay, if a man would make enquiry for <hi>Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw</hi>'s Chaplains, are they not among the the Conformiſts? Be they not alſo among them who juſtified the Murthering of the King? And if it were allowable to Glory, how many Non-conformiſts had ſuffered deeply in the Kings Cauſe before Mr. <hi>D.</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Jerſy</hi> was either baniſhed or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſted? but theſe are things wholly He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terogeneous to Conformity, and Non-conformity; So is alſo the whole ſeries of the late War: It hath been my hap as yet to know but of four meer Non-conformiſts, that were aged experienced Divines at the beginning of the Warrs; and they four ſo far as I can learn, were all in their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments unſatisfied in the Parliament War; It
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:102358:66"/>
is like enough that there were many others that were ſatisfied in their Cauſe, and acted for it: But what need Mr. <hi>D.</hi> or I be ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous about this? Does not the King under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his Supremacie? Has not the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament declared it unlawful upon any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence whatſoever to take up Arms againſt him? After ſuch Declaration, who is he that will dare to call the thing in Queſtion? I do not know that ſince his Majeſties Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn any Book has been printed, aſſerting the Lawfulneſs of Subjects taking up Arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a King, unleſs that which was publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as Mr. <hi>Hookers,</hi> by Dr. <hi>Gawden,</hi> &amp; dedicated to the King himſelfe; nor do I find any Engliſh Divine, whoſe teſtimony the Writers for the Parliaments Cauſe did more build upon, than Biſhop <hi>Bilſon,</hi> the Great Propugner of Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy, whoſe words it would be Treaſon now to tranſcribe. Mr. <hi>D.</hi> knows where to find them; let him take them into his conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and ſee how he can qualifie them; for my part I do not love to exerciſe my ſelf in things too high for me: this I muſt take leave to ſay. That Mr. <hi>D.</hi> hath mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted himſelf very groſly to be a reſpecter of perſons: for whereas he pours out con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon ſome now alive, for expreſſions that fell from them in a time of trouble and confuſion, there is ſcarce one of his beyond-Sea
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:102358:66"/>
Divines, whom he does not quote with much Honour and Reſpect, though they did in their Syſtems of Divinity, and Comments on Scripture lay down the ſame Doctrine quarrell'd at in Mr. <hi>Baxter?</hi> Doth he not know what pains <hi>David Owen</hi> hath taken to make his honeſt <hi>Calvin,</hi> and his Learned <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za,</hi> and <hi>Danaeus,</hi> &amp;c. as guilty of delivering Trayterous Doctrine as the Jeſuites them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? At leaſt he knows that <hi>Paraeus</hi> his Book was appointed to be burnt at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and yet him he makes uſe of <hi>Pag.</hi> 8th. and <hi>pag.</hi> 337. <hi>&amp;c. Andrew Rivet</hi> alſo he choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth as a man fit to be of the Synod, and yet this <hi>Rivet</hi> in his Expoſition on the 68 <hi>Pſal.</hi> determines very peremptorily for the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of defenſive Arms, and to the <hi>Ephori</hi> he allowes a liberty to take up offenſive Arms. <hi>Peter Du Moylin,</hi> and <hi>Spanhemius</hi> he would alſo have Chieftains in his Synod, And yet theſe two, the one in his Anatomy of Arminianiſme, the other in his <hi>Dubia E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelica</hi> on <hi>Matthew</hi> 5th do make the Right of Civil things to belong only to the Godly, or to the Elect, then which nothing could be ſaid more dangerous to greater or leſſer Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties. I know they both diſtinguiſh of a Right in reſpect of men, and of a Right in reſpect of God, denying onely the later unto the wicked, but giving them this grain of allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:102358:67"/>
their poſition though well meant by them, will be found neither ſound, nor ſafe; Let Mr. <hi>D.</hi> therefore warn thoſe for whom he deſigned his Book againſt this Tenent; &amp; let all men underſtand that the Engliſh Non-Conformiſts are of a quite contrary Judgment; For they ſay unanimouſly, <hi>that all wicked men</hi> have a true Right, to all that, whether Authority or Eſtate, unto which they came by due and lawful means, and that God will never puniſh them becauſe they had no right to the Eſtates they came ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to, but becauſe they did not uſe their Eſtates aright. I have onely one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt more to make to you, and by you to all your Friends, and it is a very reaſonable one, namely, that you, and they, would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther credit the Kings Declaration concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Engliſh Presbyterians, than Mr. <hi>D</hi>'s either Engliſh or Latine Book; This one deſire being granted, the Presbyterians are as ſafe as an Amulet can make them.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>You will ſay, If they only ſuffer beyond the Seas through Mr.</hi> D's <hi>miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation, why have not I ſo much Charity as to reply upon his Book, and make in Latin, as once</hi> Mr. Nichols <hi>did in Engliſh, a</hi> Plea for the Innocent?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:102358:67"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Truly Sir, becauſe I have found by Obſervation that it is in vain to diſarm him, who hath a Panoply in the very next Dunghil to which he comes, there is no dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with him; who,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Will deny matters of fact without Reaſon.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Will not take notice of the true ſtate of the Controverſie.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Will never yield though he have nothing to ſay for himſelf. Such an one is Mr. <hi>D.</hi> For if you look into his Book, you fill find him charging the Apologiſt with Fables and Legends, that is, in plain Engliſh, giving him the Lye, and yet never gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the leaſt Reaſon to perſwade the World that the things written by him were falſe. He calls it a Fable that any man ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to give Counſel &amp; adviſe to have the ſurplice after it was worn out, burnt to aſhes, the Aſhes put into an Urn, &amp; buried under the Altar; and yet this very thing I have heard ſtrongly and ſtoutly aſſerted by more than one Conformiſt, who if need require would not be aſhamed to teſtifie it publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Alſo he would have it a Fable that a man who had threatned a Miniſter for not reading the Common Prayer, ſhould being ſick ſend for him, and deſire him to pray for him, not making uſe of the Common-Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er;
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:102358:68"/>
but this as it was long ſince Printed by <hi>Giles Firmin,</hi> ſo it will be verified when he pleaſes. That Biſhop <hi>Saunderſon</hi> ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to have Prayers read him out of the whole Duty of Man, he would alſo have to be a Fable; but the Chaplain who read them, told me and others ſo, and I ſuppoſe is too honeſt a man to deny what he ſaid before ſo many.</p>
            <p>As for his not taking notice of the true ſtate of any Controverſie, I refer you to his Book to what part or parcel ſoever of it, you ſhall pleaſe to chuſe: If I miſtake not, very near his Concluſion, he has a Chap. with this Title, <hi>Whether Calvin more favoured Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical Presbyterians, or Prelates?</hi> Can you think that ever there was ſuch a Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie on foot in <hi>England?</hi> Did any one offer to ſay, that <hi>Calvin</hi> had favourable thoughts of Schiſmaticks? The Queſtion is, whether <hi>Calvin</hi> ever thought Prelacy to be by Divine appointment, an Order Superiour to Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery? And whether he would have all thoſe thrown out of the Miniſtry, who cannot ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it ſo to be; if any thing of <hi>Calvins</hi> be by Mr. <hi>D.</hi> brought to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, then will I have a quarrel againſt him that firſt taught me to conſtrue Latine: Take another inſtance, the Apologiſt had wonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that the Non-Conformiſts were put upon
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:102358:68"/>
promiſing, <hi>That they would read the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter according to the Old Engliſh Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when as we have in our Bibles a New one that is much better:</hi> he inſtanced in a few odd and uncouth Tranſlations; Now what does Mr. <hi>D.</hi> upon this? Why, he asks whether if the Tranſlation be corrupt a man ought rather to forſake his Miniſtry than to read a corrupt Tranſlation; as if the Non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts had had nothing required of them but only to read the old Tranſlation of the Pſalms; Yet I confeſs all theſe things would not diſcourage me from taking him to task, had I any hopes that he had not taught his forehead not to bluſh; but who would ſhoot at him that is become unpenetrable? I will tell you one Story: Mr. <hi>D.</hi> in the preſence of a Noble Perſon of this Nation, ſaid, <hi>That all the French Miniſtens diſowned the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Non Conformiſts in England:</hi> that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable perſon preſently replied, <hi>To my knowledge that is not ſo,</hi> Nay, <hi>Some of the French Miniſters look upon you as a kind of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtate for doing what you have done here in</hi> England. Mr. <hi>D.</hi> replying, <hi>They be onely ſome few hot-headed men that ſo think:</hi> it was preſently returned by the ſame Noble Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>Nay, the men that think ſo are very Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and worthy Divines.</hi> Yet our <hi>Vindex</hi> never changed the Copy of his Countenance, and
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:102358:69"/>
what then can you think is to be done with ſuch a man? Beſides he hath abuſed Dr. <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> the Author of the Comment upon <hi>James</hi> and <hi>Jude;</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> the Author of the <hi>Saints Everlaſting Reſt,</hi> and of the Learned <hi>Diſcourſe againſt Atheiſme and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity:</hi> and which will render him more odious beyond the Seas, he hath moſt ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully abuſed Mr. <hi>Gattaker,</hi> than whom <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> hath not had a more Learned Critick, or profund Divine: nor doth he ſpare the gray-hairs of old <hi>Gisbert Voet,</hi> the only ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving Member of the Venerable the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod of <hi>Dort;</hi> and he that ſhall dare to touch ſuch as theſe, wlll not long want a man that ſhall let him know, <hi>quid diſtent aera lupinis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For your part, my Worthy Friend, all you can deſire of me in requital of your Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility is but this, that I declare my ſelf rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy (as by theſe preſents I do) to remove a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſcruple that is left in you by the reading of that grand Volumne; ſend me that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in which you think Mr. <hi>D.</hi> hath the Non-conformiſts at the greateſt diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; If I do not return you a ſudden and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory anſwer, then ſay I have not judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed fairly and candidly concerning your Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. If you are not at leiſure to take this pains, employ our worthy friend <hi>S. E.</hi> who
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:102358:69"/>
is grown ſufficiently zealous for Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, through whoſe Pen Mr. <hi>D.</hi> to be ſure will ſuffer no diſadvantage: Let him cull out the very beſt Argument in all this <hi>Vindex</hi> his Book, if I do not forthwith reply to it, and that rationally (provided the Argument be directed againſt the Cauſe, and not againſt particular Perſons) I will then ſet a Seal up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my Lips, ſo as never more to plead in done, you of Non-Conformity; till that be the behalf will give me leave to remain, what I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>A peaceable deſirer of ſome indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence for thoſe whom I never found to be humour ſome, but Conſcientious, and Your humble Servant,</hi> W. B.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:102358:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
